<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plain relation of the late action at sea between the English &amp; Dutch, and the French fleets, from June 22 to July 5 last with reflections thereupon, and upon the present state of the nation : together with A preparation for death and a perswasive to criminals to do right to their countrey, and a specimen of a bill for reformation of manners, drawn for the bishops, and mentioned in the folowing reflections.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5434</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13699</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13587169</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13587169</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100584</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61436)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100584)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 851:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plain relation of the late action at sea between the English &amp; Dutch, and the French fleets, from June 22 to July 5 last with reflections thereupon, and upon the present state of the nation : together with A preparation for death and a perswasive to criminals to do right to their countrey, and a specimen of a bill for reformation of manners, drawn for the bishops, and mentioned in the folowing reflections.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 56, 8, 8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Harris ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Edward Stephens (Socrates Christianus).  Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100584:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PLAIN RELATION Of the Late <hi>Action at Sea,</hi> Between the <hi>ENGLISH</hi> &amp; <hi>DUTCH,</hi> and the <hi>FRENCH</hi> FLEETS, From <hi>June</hi> 22. to <hi>July</hi> 5. laſt: WITH Reflections THEREUPON, And upon the Preſent State of the Nation.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER WITH A <hi>Preparation for Death,</hi> and a <hi>Perſwaſive to Criminals to do Right to their Countrey;</hi> and a <hi>Specimen of a BILL</hi> for Reformation of Manners, drawn for the Biſhops, and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the following Reflections.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Harris</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> MDCXC.</p>
            <p>By whom alſo is Sold <hi>A Compleat Collection</hi> of the late Writings of the ſame Author, as, <hi>The true Engliſh Government,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Reflections upon the laſt Years Occurrences,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>An Apology for</hi> Mr. <hi>Stafford,</hi> &amp;c. and others for the Service of the Publick.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:100584:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100584:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHoever thou art, if thou knoweſt it not already, know, that the Author of theſe Papers is a ſincere Friend and hearty Well-wiſher to King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> the preſent Settlement, theſe Nations, and the Common Cauſe of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, as very Juſt and Honourable; and no Enemy to the late King <hi>James,</hi> the late Admiral <hi>Torrington,</hi> or to the Perſons of any of thoſe whom he believes or ſuſpects to have had an Influence in the Production of our Diſappointments; but to their Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>carriages only, that they may be duely Corrected, Reformed, and the like Prevented for the future: That he hath Written nothing malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly or falſly to his own Knowledge, but all with great Candour and Integrity for the Service
<pb facs="tcp:100584:3"/>of God, the Good of his Countrey, the Promotion of this Great and Righteous Common Cauſe, againſt a Proud Inſolent <hi>Nimrod,</hi> and for thy own Good, if thou underſtandeſt it aright. Know therefore alſo, if thou canſt be offended with him who Wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſo well to thy Countrey, and no ill to thy ſelf, thou art no good Man; and ſo wiſhing thou may<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt be better and wiſer, he bids thee heartily Farewell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THere is newly Publiſhed,</hi> The preſent State of Europe: <hi>Or, the Hiſtorical and Political Mercury: Giving an Account of all the publick and private Occurrences that are moſt conſiderable in every Court for the Month of</hi> September, 1690. <hi>with Reflections upon every State; to be continued Monthly from the Original publiſh'd at the</hi> Hague <hi>by the Authority of the States of</hi> Holland <hi>and</hi> Weſt-Friezland.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Mercury for the Month of</hi> Auguſt <hi>laſt is likewiſe done; they are both to be Sold by <hi>Iohn Harris</hi> at the</hi> Harrow <hi>in the</hi> Poultrey.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100584:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Plain Relation Of the Late <hi>Action at Sea,</hi> BETWEEN The</hi> Engliſh <hi>&amp;</hi> Dutch, <hi>and the</hi> French <hi>FLEETS, from</hi> June <hi>22. to</hi> July <hi>5. laſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ON <hi>Sunday, June</hi> the <hi>22.</hi> about Ten in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the <hi>French</hi> Fleet (which had been ſeen the <hi>Friday</hi> before off of <hi>Plimouth,</hi> and the <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> off of <hi>Portland</hi>) were ſeen from the <hi>Iſle of Wight</hi> off of <hi>Freſh-water-Bay;</hi> of which our Fleet then riding in <hi>S. Helens</hi> road had no Notice, 'till about Ten that Night from the ſhore: So that had not the Wind, which brought them with a very freſh Gale as far as <hi>Freſh-water-Bay,</hi> where they Anchored, then ſlack'd and turned Northerly, they had been in with us, and fir'd our Ships for want of Scouts out (as ſome ſay) to give Notice. But that night upon that Notice we ſtaved our Cabins, made clear our Ships, and about <hi>12.</hi> unmoor'd.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100584:4"/>
            <p>The next morning (<hi>Monday</hi> the 23d.) the Admiral hall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed home his Fore-top-ſail-ſheets, and fired a Gun to Weigh, and ſoon after all the Fleet were under ſail, and we ſtood out to Sea, and about <hi>3</hi> in the afternoon came to an Anchor, <hi>Dunnoſe, S. W.</hi> &amp; by <hi>W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next morning, (<hi>Tueſday</hi> the 24th.) betwen <hi>5</hi> and <hi>6</hi> we weighed, and ſtood to the <hi>S. E.</hi> and that Afternoon the <hi>Lyon,</hi> and ſeveral <hi>Dutch</hi> Men of War, which made them a Squadron of about <hi>17.</hi> Ships, joined us <hi>S. E.</hi> of the <hi>Iſle of Wight.</hi> And at <hi>9</hi> at night we anchored, <hi>Culver Cliff, N. W.</hi> and by <hi>W.</hi> about <hi>7</hi> Leagues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 25th. at <hi>6.</hi> in the morning we weighed, the Wind <hi>N. N. E.</hi> and about <hi>8.</hi> the Weather, which was thick before, clearing up, we ſaw the <hi>French Fleet,</hi> the Body of them bearing <hi>W. S. W.</hi> about <hi>3</hi> Leagues diſtant: And we had a fair Opportunity to engage them, the Wind <hi>S. S. E.</hi> and they under our Lee, between us and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhore, in very much Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: And in all probability had we then Engaged them, we had beaten them down upon our <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhore; our Fleet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very well provided for it, our Ships all in good Order, and our Men full of Courage and very deſirous of Action. At <hi>12. Culver Cliff, N. W.</hi> half <hi>N. 4.</hi> Leagues off, the Wind <hi>S. S. E.</hi> and between <hi>7.</hi> and <hi>8.</hi> we Anchor'd, <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſe, N. W.</hi> and by <hi>N. 5.</hi> Leagues, the <hi>French Fleet</hi> Leeward about <hi>3.</hi> Leagues.</p>
            <p>The next morning, (<hi>Thurſday</hi> the <hi>26th.</hi>) the Admiral made a Signal, and call'd a Council of Flagg-Officers; where it was agreed not to fight the <hi>French,</hi> ſuppoſing them too ſtrong for us, but to plye to the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> (the Wind being <hi>E.</hi>) as far as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100584:4"/>the Flats of the Foreland, and there intangle them in the Sands, rather than fight them; but yet to keep ſight of them, leaſt they ſhould land; which notwithſtanding we did not, but plyed out of ſight, ſo that they might have landed if they would.</p>
            <p>From that time he kept turning to the <hi>E.</hi> every Tide from day to day, (which the <hi>French</hi> obſerving, kept turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after) 'till <hi>Sunday</hi> Evening, the Wind continuing Eaſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all that time, inſomuch that the Seamen being greatly diſcontented at it, began to murmur and exclaime againſt him for it: But then a Signal was made for a Council of the Flagg-Officers, where it was reſolved to Fight the <hi>French</hi> the next day, but no Notice thereof was given to any of the Fleet beſides.</p>
            <p>The next Morning being <hi>Munday</hi> the <hi>30th.</hi> the Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal was given for a Line of Battle, when moſt of our Ships having no Notice before were unprepared; yet our Men threw up their Caps, and ſhewed all demonſtrations of Joy at the Notice, and made ready as faſt as they could; and, (the <hi>French</hi> probably ſuppoſing we had ſtill kept turning to the <hi>E.</hi> as we did before, and therefore turning after) both Fleets came near about Eight that Morning in two Lines croſs the Channel, our Fleet ſtanding about <hi>4</hi> Leagues to the <hi>Weſt</hi> of the <hi>Beachy-Head,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſquadron in the Van toward the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhore, the Red in the Body, the Blew in the Rear toward the <hi>French</hi> Coaſt; and the Bloody Flag being hoiſted before, about <hi>9.</hi> both Fleets came to Engage.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> (leading the Van) and part of the Blew (in the Rear) joining near them made them give way; but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100584:5"/>the Red (except two or three Ships) not going ſo near as they ſhould, (but ſtanding aloof, which brought our Fleet into the form of a Half moon,) the Body of the <hi>French</hi> Fleet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving none to engage them, made up with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and did them great Damage; whereas at the ſame time the Rear of the <hi>French</hi> ran from thoſe of the Blew who fought them.</p>
            <p>The Admiral, as I am inform'd by one of his Ship, fired many Guns; but as moſt agree, ſtood at that diſtance, that no Man can tell to what purpoſe it was, unleſs to waſt Powder and Shot. There were others alſo of our Fleet, as it is affirmed, which lay to the Windward and fired over our own Ships, and did ſome of them no little Damage; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that our Sea-men were very much exaſperated at it.</p>
            <p>The Engagement continued till about five of the Clock; but then the <hi>French</hi> bore away, and ſo put an end to the Action of that Day; and both Fleets Anchored that Night.</p>
            <p>The next Morning both Fleets lay at Anchor, looking one upon the other, as if neither had any Inclination to fight. And it is believed that had not the <hi>Engliſh</hi> made the haſte from them, which they did, they might very well have ſent away the diſabled Ships, and ſaved them; and the <hi>French</hi> would never have attack'd us.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Engagement</hi> the <hi>French</hi> had one of that Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, which fought the Blew, ſunk, and the Quarter of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blown up, as is affirmed by many; beſides what other loſs they had, which is believed to have been conſiderable, eſpecially from the <hi>Dutch</hi> Squadron, which is generally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100584:5"/>to have behaved themſelves very bravely, thô the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars are not yet known to us: But <hi>1500</hi> Men kill'd and wounded they themſelves confeſs, and Intelligence from <hi>France</hi> informs us that they had divers Veſſels very much ſhattered. On our ſide there was not one Ship loſt in the Fight, unleſs one of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> (concerning which there is ſome difference in Relations) only the <hi>Ann</hi> of the Blew, and about ſeven of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> which were afterward burnt, and poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſome others, were diſabled.</p>
            <p>But on <hi>Tueſday</hi> Morning, <hi>as ſome ſay,</hi> a Dutch Vice-Admiral being diſabled, the Men finding themſelves among the <hi>French,</hi> fired their Ship, and got off to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhore, to the Weſt of <hi>Shoram;</hi> which others ſay was fired the Day or Night before. But the <hi>Ann,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Dutch</hi> diſabled Ships, were towed into our Fleet, out of danger for the preſent: But that Night the Admiral having ordered the <hi>Swallow</hi> and the <hi>York</hi> to towe the <hi>Ann,</hi> commanded all to turn to the Windward: whereupon one of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships being left by the Fleet, the Men were forced the <hi>next Day</hi> to burn the Ship, and get on ſhore as they could, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where about <hi>Shoram;</hi> for the <hi>French</hi> obſerving the Motion of our Fleet, as they turned, turned after them.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Thurſday</hi> three more of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships being like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe left, were forced to do the like at or near <hi>Haſtings:</hi> and the Captain of the <hi>Ann</hi> (which, as ſome ſay, had been towed three Leagues to the <hi>E.</hi> of our Fleet, and was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to bear into our Fleet again) being alſo left, was forced to make a Waff and fire a Gun; and the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100584:6"/>thereupon ſending his Yat, the Captain ſent him word, that unleſs he ſent them more Aſſiſtance, they ſhould be in danger to fall into the hands of the Enemy; whereunto the Admiral returned Anſwer, That they muſt take what courſe they could to ſave themſelves, for he could not help them; and ſo kept on turning to Windward, which the Enemy ſtill obſerving, as he turned, turned after him: ſo that upon <hi>Friday</hi> another of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships was forced to do as their Fellows had done, fire their Ship, and get on ſhore near <hi>Haſting.</hi> And upon the <hi>Saturday</hi> the <hi>Ann</hi> for want of Aſſiſtance was forced to do the like between <hi>Haſting</hi> and <hi>Rye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas had the Admiral and his Squadron fought as the reſt did, we had undoubtedly obtain'd a conſiderable Victory over the <hi>French</hi> Fleet with leſs Loſs than we have now ſuſtained: However, he might eaſily have ſaved thoſe Ships which were fired on Wedneſday and afterward, had he but kept his ſtation, and not by turning as he did, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited the <hi>French</hi> to the Honour of following, and the Pleaſure of beholding the deſerted <hi>Dutch</hi> day after day firing their own Ships, leſt they ſhould fall into their hands.</p>
            <div type="narrative">
               <p>This Relation was firſt taken from the Information of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Voluntier Seaman, who was in the Fleet all the time above mentioned, and in the Engagement; and afterward compleated from the Informations of divers others who were alſo in the Fight, and in the Fleet, all the time aforeſaid. And for the <hi>Readers</hi> more full ſatisfaction I will here ſubjoin in <hi>Engliſh</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100584:6"/>
            <head>A Copy of a Letter written to the <hi>(French)</hi> Court from on Board M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>de Tourville.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>MOunſieur</hi> de Chateau Renault, <hi>who commanded the Rear-Guard compoſed of</hi> 21 <hi>Ships, had this day the Van-Guard; the Blew Squadron of</hi> 25 <hi>Ships was the Body of the Battel; and the Count</hi> d'Eſtree, <hi>whoſe Squadron was</hi> 23 <hi>Ships, had the Rear-Guard. As to the Enemies, the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Red, commanding the Red Squadron, had the Body of the Battel compoſed of</hi> 22. <hi>Ships; the</hi> Hollanders <hi>to the number of</hi> 22. <hi>Ships, led the Van Guard; and the Blew Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of</hi> 16 <hi>Ships, had the Rear-Guard. They immediately ſtretch'd out their Line. The</hi> Hollanders <hi>firſt charg'd our Van-Guard, and they had already diſcharg'd their Broad-ſides, when the Sieur</hi> Herbert, <hi>call'd</hi> E. of Torrington, <hi>who commanded the Body of the Battel, came to attack ours. It was believ'd at that time that he would have ſought out Mounſ.</hi> de Tourville <hi>to fight with him, but inſtead of acting in that manner, and as became a brave Admiral, he ſtop'd at the laſt Ship of the White Squadron, and the Marqueſs</hi> d' Amfreville, <hi>who was the Rear-Admiral, had to do with the common Seamen, before with</hi> Herbert,
<note place="margin">Eut à faire aux Matet lots, avan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu'a Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert.</note> 
               <hi>who e'en withdrew himſelf in leſs than half an hour. Never was ſeen a fairer Veſſel than that Red Admiral, and ſo ill commanded. And Mounſ.</hi> Herbert <hi>loſt this Expedition the little Reputation he had remaining before. He did not ſhoot but at a diſtance, and althô he had the Advantage of the Wind, yet he never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached within Cannon-ſhot. By this means our Diviſion, which ſhould have ſuſtain'd the greateſt Fire, loſt not above</hi> 5 <hi>men on board the</hi> Magnificent, <hi>and ſome Shot in her Maſts. The</hi> Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers <hi>attack'd our Van-guard very vigorouſly; but</hi> Herbert <hi>willing to ſacrifice them, althô he ſaw them fight like brave men, and both Tiers of our Fleet ſlaughtering of them, never did his endeavour to ſuccour them; but on the contrary, retired out of Cannon-ſhot. We have not loſt in this Fight any Perſon of Note, except the Chevalier</hi> de Clermont: <hi>The</hi> Agreeable, <hi>the</hi> Fleuron, <hi>and the</hi> Moderate, <hi>are the Ships which have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the moſt: As to the kill'd and wounded, we have had about Fifteen hundred.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:100584:7"/>
            <p>And now ſhould we enter into <hi>a Computation</hi> of the particulars of our Loſs, we might ſet them down under ſeveral Heads, ſuch as theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimis. Lucrum ceſſans,</hi> The Loſs of a great Advantage we had to have gotten a compleat Victory over the <hi>French</hi> Fleet: as is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent by what was done by that part of our Fleet which fought, and not only withſtood the force of their whole Fleet, but made them bear away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item. Damnum emergens,</hi> Loſs actually ſuſtain'd in ſeveral re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. As,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It.</hi> Of Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It.</hi> Of Ships.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It.</hi> Of Rigging, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It.</hi> Of Honour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It.</hi> Of Time and Expences in refitting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It.</hi> Of Trade, while the <hi>French</hi> ride Maſters at Sea.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It.</hi> Diſtraction of the Countrey from their Harveſt to ſerve in the Militia, upon Occaſion of the <hi>French</hi> Fleet lying upon our Coaſt, to the great Charge of the Countrey.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It.</hi> The Advantages gotten by our Enemies, which may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted as a Loſs to us; ſuch as theſe,
<list>
                  <item>1. Of Honour.</item>
                  <item>2. Of Courage, they being animated by it.</item>
                  <item>3. Of Leiſure and Opportunity.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It.</hi> Diſappointment for ſome time of the entire reducing of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> proceeding from the Enemies Apprehenſions of our Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment at Sea, which occaſions the greater Charge and longer Diverſion of our Forces from other Service; beſides the hazard of what may happen in the mean time, or upon that occaſion.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Much of this Loſs is a Loſs, not only to the King, and to this Nation, but to <hi>the Common Intereſt of the Confederates:</hi> So that the King and this State are obliged, not only in Honour and Prudence for themſelves, but alſo in Juſtice to the Confederates, and eſpecially to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who behaved themſelves ſo bravely, were ſo baſely deſerted, and thereby ſuffered ſo much, to enquire impartially into the Miſcarriages, and puniſh them as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="reflection">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100584:7"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS Upon the Precedent Relation,</head>
            <p>IN the Occurrences of the laſt Year, we had beſides the Loſs of our Expence only a kind of <hi>Lucrum ceſſans,</hi> a Diſappointment in the Opportunities and Advantages we had to have promoted our own Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement and the common Cauſe, to compute: And therefore, as it was the more eaſie, for any one, who thought fit to apply his mind to it, to invent ſome plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Pretences to cover the Miſcarriages, which were then committed in the Management of Affairs; ſo ſuch Pretences then would the more eaſily paſs, with ſuch as were more concerned to keep fair with all Men for their own advantage, than to promote the Publick Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of their Countrey and the common Cauſe, eſpecially by any ſuch Means as might poſſibly produce any Prejudice or Diſadvantage to their own. But beſides all this, in the late Action at Sea, when the Heavens had favoured us, firſt with a ſpecial Deliverance from a very dangerous Surprize, and then with as favourable Advantage as our Hearts could wiſh, and that continued for many dayes together, not only to neglect the ſame, to neglect it though provoked, by the Courage and by the Danger alſo of our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100584:8"/>Allies, and of ſome of our own Ships beſides; but moreover to deſert ſuch as were diſabled, and ſo deſert as by turning againſt the Wind to invite and animate the Enemy, (who of themſelves it ſeems had otherwiſe no mind to it, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expected a more vigorous Engagement of our whole Fleet) to follow and triumphantly ſeize or deſtroy them, is ſuch a Miſcarriage, and that aggravated with ſo great a Loſs, Damage, and miſchievous and dangerous Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, as requires a Perſon of rare Invention, of equal Impudence, and void of all ſenſe of Honour and Love to his Countrey, to compoſe a Vindication of this Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ſo much as with Confidence and hope of Succeſs endeavour to cover it; and People of no leſs ſtupidity and eaſineſs to be impoſed upon by ſuch Pretences. Indeed the <hi>Miſcarriage</hi> was ſo groſs and palpable, as moved the Indignation even of ſome of the Vindicators of the laſt Years Tranſactions to reſlect with ſome warmth upon it, and extorted their Remarks upon the ill Conſequences of ſuch Miſcarriages as were before palliated: Such in ſhort as none will offer to excuſe, who are not either Partners in the Crime, or no good Friends to the Cauſe; or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any Excuſe who are not either ſuch, or ſuch as are too apt and eaſie to be impoſed upon by ſmooth Tongues and fallacious Pretences of others.</p>
            <p>And as the Miſcarriage is too groſs to be covered, ſo is <hi>the Loſs, Damage, and evil Conſequence</hi> thereof too great to be buryed in Oblivion. In point of <hi>Honour</hi> it ought to be enquired into ſtrictly, to the bottom, and puniſhed ſeverely, for ſatisfaction to <hi>the World;</hi> and in point of <hi>Juſtice</hi> no leſs, for ſatisfaction to all <hi>our Confederates</hi> in the ſame common Cauſe, which ſuffers much by the Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment; but more eſpecially <hi>the Dutch,</hi> who beſide have ſuſtained ſo conſiderable a Loſs peculiar to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: And certainly no leſs ought to be done in point both of <hi>Juſtice and Intereſt</hi> for ſatisfaction at home, both to <hi>the whole Nation</hi> in general, not well pleaſed to ſee their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100584:8"/>Trade thus at a ſtand, and their Money the while waſted upon a Company of debanched, impious, wicked Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, for two Years together, with ſo little effect; and more particularly to the <hi>Sea-men,</hi> who think it hard, that they who are Free men, and willing to ſerve their Countrey under Officers whom they like, ſhould be preſſed and forced, as if they were Gally ſlaves, to ſerve under ſuch as they think neither otherwiſe well-qualified, nor very good Friends either to them, or to the Cauſe they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage in. To all which we muſt add another Point of <hi>Prudence</hi> to prevent the like for the future, by Caſhiering at leaſt ſuch as are found guilty, or not well qualified for the Service, however they came by their Places; and by good Examples of neceſſary Diſcipline to deterr others from undertaking what they are not ſit for, or from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting or neglecting what they have once undertaken. And certainly that to which ſo many Obligations and conſiderable Motives concurr, muſt needs be very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: and it would therefore be a great ſign of a very weak and languiſhing State, to let ſo great and miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous a Miſcarriage be lightly paſſed over under the cover of ſuch ſuperficial Pretences as every Tarpaulin and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sea-man can ſee through, without ſome proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Animadverſion upon the Delinquents, and effectual Purgation and Reformation of the Fleet upon ſo notorious an occaſion.</p>
            <p>All this Miſchief, I know, is commonly imputed to our Admiral <hi>Torrington.</hi> Not only the Letter printed in the <hi>French Gazet</hi> from the E. of <hi>Nottingham</hi> to my Lord <hi>Durſley</hi> in <hi>Holland;</hi> but a Relation printed in <hi>France,</hi> as I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, by that Kings Authority, lays it chiefly upon him. The Letter, amongſt other Paſſages concerning the Fight, hath one to this effect: <hi>The</hi> Holland <hi>Squadron be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved it ſelf with ſo much Bravery, that if my Lord</hi> Torring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton <hi>had done his Duty, we ſhould in all probability have had a Compleat Victory; but at preſent we retreat before the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:100584:9"/>Which is in few words the ſumme of what the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the honeſt Seaman hath more particularly inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, and no little Confirmation of it.</p>
            <p>And indeed he being ſo notoriouſly faulty, it cannot be expected that vulgar Spectators ſhould look any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the matter, but be well ſatisfied with the juſt Puniſhment of him alone: For whoever elſe might be concerned in it, they at Land being out of the Action, may be thought far enough out of Suſpicion; and they who at Sea were in the Action, (if it may be proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo ſaid of them who ſtood ſtill and acted not at all, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in retreating from the Enemy,) they have a fair pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of his Authority to cover their own Miſcarriages. And yet poſſibly none of them may be ſo ſecure as they thought themſelves: For his Honour is now ſo broken by this Miſcarriage, and his caſe ſo deſparate, that I know not what ſhould or can oblige or reſtrain him, not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge himſelf of ſo much of the <hi>Odium,</hi> as is properly due to thoſe, who by any means either induced him to, or concurred with him in ſo baſe, diſhonourable, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous a Miſcarriage; or impoſe upon him either to ſuffer himſelf to be abuſed and <hi>Colemanized</hi> with vain hopes and expectations; or tamely bear the burden of others no better than himſelf, who by unfaithful concurrence at leaſt, were ſome occaſion of his Unhappineſs: and 'tis like, when he is once gone, will be as forward as any to caſt dirt upon his Memory, to clear themſelves of all ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. And if his Affliction, as ſometimes it doth, ſhould awaken in him any ſenſe of Religion, Repentance, Juſtice, or love to his Countrey, all theſe do plainly oblige him to detect all: He can certainly make no ſuch ſtep toward a reparation to his King and Countrey, as by detecting thoſe who have already been unfaithful, or are unfit for ſuch a truſt; that being difcharged, and otherwiſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed as they deſerve, they may be prevented from doing the like miſchief for the future. And for them it is in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100584:9"/>truth (though this brutiſh, ſenſual Generation are not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of it) much better, that they ſhould be judged here, accept of their Puniſhment, and bear their Iniquity, than be condemned hereaf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er.</p>
            <p>But to retorn, that none ſhould be culpable in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs but <hi>Lorrington,</hi> doth not at all ſeem probable to me. He was indeed the Principal in the Miſcarriage, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had Authority ſufficient to have prevented it, or at leaſt to ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e done ſo much as muſt have left ſome others inexcuſable: But it is not likely he would have behaved himſelf as he did, if he had not had ſome Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, at leaſt by a willing and eaſie compliance. And it's likely, if the truth were known, there were ſeveral <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſartes,</hi> not only at Sea, but at Land alſo. Such was the Behaviour of others at Sea, that the eamen generally blame the Officers, very few excepted. And when the Commiſſioners, who were ſent to examine the matter, ſat at <hi>Sheerneſs,</hi> it was <hi>obſerved,</hi> 
               <hi rend="margQuotes">That ſeveral of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers had prepared an Account of the Action in writing under their hands, calculated for the Intereſt of <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington,</hi> and were very high and upiſh in the morning, and carried it toweringly, and jarring with ſome of the Blew Squadron; though when they came after to be examined upon their Oaths, (which it was gueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed they did not expect,) and ſome of the Blew ſpake their Judgments freely, their Carriage was obſerved to be much altered, and they looked more calmly.</hi> And upon the whole matter, there were ſome <hi>Obſervations</hi> then made, which are very proper to be here inſerted: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That a great part of the Commanders of this Fleet are abſolute</hi> Creatures of Torrington: <hi>Otherwiſe, if they had been Men of Freedom and Principles, they would have been more forward to have made their Complaints againſt him. And if it be found a Fault in him, all thoſe muſt be Fools or Knaves, that either did not See it, or endeavoured to Excuſe it. And to ſpeak plain, many of thoſe Gentlemen are eſteemed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100584:10"/>to underſtand better how to Dreſs, and to Eat, and Drink well,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>than to perform a Charge, which requires great Diſcretion and Reſolution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Conduct of</hi> thoſe Gentlemen <hi>may be reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon,</hi> that have ſuffered <hi>one Perſon almoſt to fill the Fleet with his own Creatures, and ſhewn no more regard to the Qualifications of Vertue and Merit, than to preferr many Men meerly for Favour and Affection, or according to the time they have ſerved in the Fleet: So that there are in ſome ſecond and third Rates, Men that have given little or no Proof of their Worth, when others that have eminently diſtinguiſhed themſelves, have either been wholly neglected, or put into ſmall Ships.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That this ſort of Commanders are grown to a</hi> kind of Faction, <hi>and make it their Endeavour to introduce Men of their own Stamp into thoſe Employments, maintaining a kind of Animoſity and Hatred againſt thoſe Perſons who are not of their Temper, and are put into Men of War for the ſake of their Experience or Merit. Than which there can can be no readier way to introduce a Dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy from Virtue and Bravery in our Navy, and to loſe our Ancient Reputation for Maritine Performances, when the Management ſhall come into the Hands of men of lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Experience or Conduct. Of which our late Diſgrace is too freſh an Inſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That many of theſe Commanders are ſo</hi> hated by the Seamen, <hi>that a Mutiny is rather to be apprehended from them, than a going chearfully to adventure their Lives with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That able</hi> Seamen <hi>are much wanting in the Fleet, and the</hi> Ships <hi>will require longer fitting than is talked of; ſo that I ſcarcely expect this Fleet can goe out this Month.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>That if this</hi> Commiſſion <hi>of Enquiry were continued, with the addition of two or three more Perſons, as</hi> Aſſiſtants <hi>who were well skilled in Maritine Affairs, and could not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100584:10"/>be impoſed upon by fraudulent Anſwers, or invented Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, there might be</hi> matter enough <hi>found to charge</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Officers, <hi>and ſhew that there is an abſolute neceſſity of making a great</hi> Reform <hi>in the Fleet, and no leſs in the Office of Admiralty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>That untill we are ſo Reformed, I dare preſume to ſay, without pretending to be a Prophet, that we ſhall never regain our l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the Obſervations, which were made at that time, intire as they came to my hand. By which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>leman who made them, whoever he was, was of the ſame Opinion, that there were Acceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries at Land as well as at Sea to this Miſcarriage. And it is probable that there were more than he had then occaſion to reflect upon, and ſuch as were really and properly Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries in that particular Miſcarriage: Such as it is very fit, upon all the Conſiderations before mentioned, that the State ſhould inquire of.</p>
            <p>But 'tis likely there are ſome who are and have been <hi>Acceſſaries,</hi> it may be more remotely, and therefore not ſo eaſie to be charged; yet no leſs effectual, but rather <hi>Prime Cauſes</hi> in this and all the reſt of our Diſappointments both of this and the laſt Year; and, which is worſe, are like ſtill ſo to be, in more for the future, unleſs the <hi>Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> thereof be ſpeedily taken into good Conſideration, and with great ſteadineſs and Reſolution as effectually reformed and prevented as may be.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> thereby done to this Nation, and to the Common Cauſe, are greater already than moſt Men are well aware of We have promoted nothing, are in no better a condition than we were in the Spring laſt was twelve month. Our Condition has been much like that of a bewitched Cart, we have whip'd, and heav'd, and made a great ſtir, and yet are in effect but where we were, if <hi>Ireland</hi> was now wholly reduced: For it might certainly have been reduced at firſt with leſs difficulty than
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100584:11"/>the taking of <hi>Limrick</hi> now at laſt. <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> then wanted only ſome body to quit it to, with ſome ſuch Force and Power, that he might do it honourably. It is not to be doubted but there were ſome <hi>Huſhat</hi>'s then about the King, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>k the Occaſion of his being a Stranger, to impoſe upon him with ſpecious dilatory Counſels, Miſieproſentations of things, and ill Recommendations of Perſons, which was the more eaſie then to be done, when moſt of our great Men were ſo intent upon improving the Opportunity for their own peculiar Advantage, that they minded little elſe, 'till they had ſecured what they could for themſelves.</p>
            <p>But this is not all; beſides the Loſs of ſo much <hi>Time,</hi> we have loſt a great many <hi>Lives;</hi> more without doing any thing, than were neceſſary to have ſecured the whole Countrey at firſt: We have loſt much of our <hi>Trade,</hi> not only at Sea, but at Land alſo, as much as depends upon our Trade at Sea; and alſo loſt vaſtly in what we had out before, and was returning home, or ſent out ſince; and beſides loſt it <hi>to our Enemies,</hi> which makes it in effect a double loſs to us: And, (which by that means falls the heavyer upon the Nation) have not done what we have done at laſt, without ſo great <hi>Expence</hi> as will make our Supplies come ſo much the harder. And all theſe are Loſſes actually ſuſtain'd: But in a true and juſt Eſtimate of the Miſchief, the <hi>Hazards and Dangers</hi> it hath brought us into, ought alſo to be computed; the common Hazard of War; the great Trouble that a Diſappointment at firſt in that Expedition might have occaſioned; and the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of his Majeſties Perſon to prevent it: And one more, which is of very great importance, but ſuch as few are ſo ſenſible of it as it deſerves, and that is the Confederacy, leſt a Diſſolution, or ſuch Interruption therein as may retard their Proceedings, ſhould happen: Which, all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, may very eaſily be; and that makes the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Opportunity the more valuable and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o much the more aggravates the Miſcarriage of thoſe who hinder
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100584:11"/>it. And though no ſuch hath yet happened, yet are we by this means ſtill in more and more danger of it, both by reaſon of the Charges of the War ſo long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and of many unexpected Accidents, which may oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr before the next Summer. I ſay nothing here of the great Opportunity and Advantage of proceeding againſt <hi>France,</hi> then under a great Conſternation, which was loſt: becauſe it is not underſtood or conſidered, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps will be believed. And without that, the other Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs and Diſappointments we have had, and may ſtill expect, if the Occaſions be not removed, are ſufficient to make all that have any ſenſe and concern look about them.</p>
            <p>The immediate <hi>Occaſions</hi> of theſe Diſappointments, which have all proceeded from the Miſcarriages of the Perſons imployed, were the imploying of ſuch Perſons as were not duely qualified: And this leads us directly to <hi>the Perſons who imployed them;</hi> that is, who either by Authority, or by Recommendation were the immediate Cauſes or Occaſions that they were imployed. It is true, they were all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by the King, in ſome reſpect, as by his Authority, but all or moſt either immediately by others, who were intruſted and Commiſſioned by him, or at leaſt by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendations, Perſwaſions or Advice of others: And if any of theſe did act therein upon any ſiniſter reſpects, they were really and effectually Acceſſaries to the Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which proceeded from the Miſcarriages of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo imployed.</p>
            <p>Now what <hi>Siniſter Reſpects</hi> might prevail in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and might therefore be the <hi>Original Occaſions</hi> of the Employment of ſuch Perſons, is not hard to be perceived by any Man who conſiders the preſent Diſpoſition of a great part of this Nation, and eſpecially of thoſe who ſouffle for Places, or are very forward to catch at them. There was not any Vice more propagated by the Evil Example of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, than <hi>Greedineſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100584:12"/>and Knavery.</hi> The Nation was cheated of their Money, by corrupting their Truſtees, (their Repreſentatives in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;) which was one of the greateſt Knaveries that could be practiſed: And this came at laſt to ſome of the groſſeſt, Shut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> ſeizing peoples Charity for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of Slaves, and ſurprizing the <hi>Dutch Smyrna</hi> Fleet. And by ſuch means were thoſe about him taught to do the like, and even to cheat himſelf; which produced ſuch a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Corruption in that reſpect, that Cheating and Knavery came into Faſhion, and was affected, ſo it could be done neatly, as a recommendation of Wit and Parts; and <hi>Honeſty and Plain-dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> was deſpiſed as Ignorance of the World, and Folly: And ſo notorious were the Frauds and Cheats practiſed in his Reign, as had never been known in this Nation before. But this was not all, it had this other pernicious Influence, that many even of thoſe, who were not corrupted by it, ſo far as to plain Knavery, were yet plainly thereby infected with inſatiable Avarice and Over-valuation of the things of the World; and thoſe generous and heroick Virtues of Piety and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Faith, which overcomes the World, which make Men more active for the Service of God and their Countrey, than for the Advancement of themſelves or their Families in Eſtates or Honour among Men; were either totally extinguiſhed and ſuppreſſed, or at leaſt deſpiſed and reproach'd, if they dared to appear with any confidence of their Innocence and Sincerity, as Folly, Madneſs, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſm, Fanaticiſm, Precipitant Zeal, Indiſcretion, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly, and whatever the ſelfiſh temporizing Genius of the times could imagine: And the only <hi>Wiſdom then in Faſhion</hi> was Self-preſervation, and Self-ſeeking Pretences of Loyalty and Zeal for the Government; and Self-Intereſt paſſed current, as an excuſable, if not commendable End of all Mens Actions: But the improvement of all Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, and making the beſt of ones own, was unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. And ſuch in particular was the <hi>Selling of Places, receiving of Gratifications</hi> for them, or <hi>conferring them by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100584:12"/>way of Gratification,</hi> or <hi>for Affection</hi> to Relations or Friends, without much regard to the Service of the Publick. This had ſo far prevailed then, and excited ſuch Emulation and Appetite in moſt Spectators, and many who were then kept off at a diſtance, that it is not credible that it ſhould have ceaſed of it ſelf ſince the late Revolution, which brought many new Incentives with it, but hath not yet produced any ſuch Charms as were like to lay it. This therefore may very well be believed to be <hi>one of theſe Siniſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects</hi> which may have prevailed in this Caſe: And as there is no ſmall reaſon from what I have ſaid to believe it, ſo I find it commonly believed by thoſe, who in all probability little conſidering theſe things which I have now mentioned, muſt therefore have ſome other reaſons from matter of Fact for their belief. We have ſeen Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks upon the ill Conſequences of Buying and Selling of Offices lately publiſhed in Print, and by a publick Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencer, who had either reaſon to believe that it is our own Caſe, or his Remarks were very impertinent, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impertinent but ſomething worſe; and if he did believe it, his expreſſing himſelf as far from granting any ſuch Practices to be in uſe here in <hi>England,</hi> ſavours more of that vulgar Wiſdom lately in faſhion, than of thoſe Virtues I mentioned before. For my own part I was never privy to any ſuch Negotiations, and therefore can ſay nothing of it of my own particular knowledge; but for the reaſons before mentioned, and others, beſides com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon report upon the Obſervation of the courſe of our Affairs, I make no queſtion of it. And this I can ſay, that when not long ſince I recommended a Perſon, who was a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to me, but I underſtood by others, and by a Certificate under his Captains hand, had behaved himſelf well in the laſt Eagagement, and deſerved Preferment, to a Noble Lord, to be by him recommended to the Commiſſioners of the Admiralty, I underſtood by him that ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendations were not well taken there. Which, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100584:13"/>looks to me as a ſign of ſome Siniſter Reſpects too prevalent amongſt them; for otherwiſe ſuch Recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of ſuch Perſons is a thing deſirable for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Service of the King and Kingdom. And I hope the late Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages at Sea will make this buſineſs be more narrowly looked into for the future: For I cannot think that <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington</hi> alone could ever have done ſo great Miſchief, if there had not been others too ready to comply with him. And to conclude this matter, I look upon <hi>Inſatiable Deſire of the ſuperfluous things of the World</hi> to be one of the great Corruptions of all ſorts of People of this Nation at this time, and a principal Impediment of generous Actions for the Publick Good, even in thoſe who are otherwiſe Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſhers to it.</p>
            <p>They, who have ſo little ſenſe of the Concerns of their Countrey, as to diſpoſe of Publick Places and Offices of Truſt for private Gain to themſelves, will be apt to do as much for <hi>Favour and Affection</hi> to their private Friends and Relations, without regard to their Merit or Qualifications for the Service of the Publick. But beſides theſe, there is another ſiniſter Reſpect, which is very prevalent upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who it may be ſcorn to take Money upon any ſuch account, and uſually impoſeth upon them under the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Service to the Publick, to the King and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and that is <hi>Faction.</hi> This hath had no ſmall ſhare in the introducing of many very ill men into Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, and keeping out many very good, cordially affected to the Government, and as well qualified for the Service; and by theſe, and other Means beſides, hath been a principal Occaſion of retarding our Progreſs, and of the Diſappointments we have met with.</p>
            <p>This Nation hath been long peſtered with a Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of two pernicious Factions, and from them and the Principles of their generation, hath lately upon the late Revolution proceeded a third; and that the moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of all: So that now it is become a <hi>Tripple Faction,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:100584:13"/>a Beaſt with three Heads, according to the Sacred Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations of ſuch things. The two former were the Old Court Faction, and the Old Church Faction. The third, which hath riſen of late, do moſt of them agree with the former in other matters; but being perſwaded that King <hi>James</hi> could not any way forfeit his Right, nor did really abdicate it, believe he hath ſtill a Right; and yet not ſatisfied to ſit ſtill and enjoy their Eſtates, their Rights, their Religion, and their Conſciences under the preſent Settlement in quiet, and be thankful to God for their Deliverance from thoſe dangerous Conſpiracies which began to be put in practice, (as divers worthy Perſons, who have otherwiſe the ſame ſentiments with themſelves do,) will needs engage in ſuch Employments as oblige them to act in Council, or in War againſt him, whom notwitſtanding they believe to be their King <hi>de Jure:</hi> And thus while they own two Maſters, and cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſerve both, they are in great danger to ſerve nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faithfully.</p>
            <p>As to the diſpoſing of Places, they all agree in this, to keep out all they can, who are not of their Party, though otherwiſe never ſo cordial Friends to K. <hi>William</hi> and Qu. <hi>Mary,</hi> and the preſent Settlement, never ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the Common Cauſe, never ſo well qualified for the Service, never ſo Pious and Vertuous, if they be not of the Party or Faction: But be they but zealous for the intereſt of their Party, thô they be never ſo vitious, debauch'd or profane; never ſo empty and ſhallow, never ſo blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering and inconſiderate, never ſo meanly qualified, they ſhall be embraced as honeſt Men, nay, as good Church of <hi>England</hi> Men, and recommended to ſerve not only in Parliament, (for which there are none now who think not themſelves ſufficiently qualified) but other Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of greateſt weight and moment. And while they all agree to keep out all that are not of their party, this new Faction take care to bring in as many as they can
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100584:14"/>of theirs; that is, ſuch as acknowledging King <hi>James</hi> his Right ſtill to remain and continue, are not ſatisfied to enjoy their own in quiet, but for their own advantage will pretend and undertake to act againſt him. By theſe means is the King and Kingdom deprived of the Service of a great part of the beſt and moſt ſerviceable of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and our Offices and Places are filled with Perſons of no Worth, or of as little Affection to the Service; and ſuch as are apt upon occaſion by ſecret Services, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratiate themſelves with King <hi>James;</hi> and ſo wiſe, as not to diſoblige him by overacting to his prejudice, when they can with any colour avoid it. And how any great Work managed by people ſo affected to it, is like to ſucceed, is no hard matter to gueſs.</p>
            <p>That this is plainly our Caſe, cannot, I am perſwaded, but be caſily perceived by all Parties; by ſome with no little ſatisfaction, and by others with no leſs Indignation and Trouble, to ſee ſo Noble, and at firſt ſo proſperous a Cauſe, thus obſtructed and diſappointed by a mixture of vitious and careleſs, and of treacherous and unfaithful People; while others, who are both ſerious and heartily affected to it, are kept out of the Service. But how it may moſt effectually be helped, is not ſo eaſily appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, nor well underſtood. Two or three things there are which may be propoſed with a great deal of Reaſon, and I confeſs do deſerve to be well conſidered; yet if we look no farther, I am well ſatisfied, will either never be effected, or if they be, will never of themſelves pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Effects expected from them.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, that the King, who hath ſo far expoſed his own Royal Perſon to danger for us, and for the common Cauſe of the Confederates, may not be longer deprived of the Service of ſuch as are his ſincere Friends, and ready to do the like for him, for it, and for the whole Nation, by a ſuperfluous clauſe in the letter of the Law, no way neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the declared ſcope of it. I mean the Stat. 25. <hi>Car.</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:100584:14"/>2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. which among other things enacts, <hi>That all and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Perſon and Perſons ſo to be admitted as aforeſaid, ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo receive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper <hi>according to the uſage of the Church of England,</hi> within three months after his or their Admittance in, or receiving their ſaid Authority and Employment, <hi>in ſome publick Church,</hi> upon ſome Lord's Day, commonly called Sunday, immediately after Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Sermon.</hi> This Act was made for preventing Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, which then might happen from Popiſh Recuſants, as appears by the Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, is declared in the very beginning of the Act, and is emphatically expreſſed by the words <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Recuſants,</hi> which reſtrain it to them alone of all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters. And though there be ſome words, as, <hi>according to the uſage of the Church of</hi> England, and, <hi>in ſome Publick Church,</hi> which reſtrain the admittance to Conformiſts on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; yet it is plain, that that reſtraint neither was neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, nor was deſigned by the Act for that purpoſe, or in order to that end: and therefore conſidering the Practice of thoſe Times, it is not to be doubted but they were put in partly by the Papiſts, to divide the Proteſtants in that as well as in matters of Religion, that ſo they might have a party of Proteſtants in the ſame condition with themſelves, which was a very common Policy among them, and partly by the Faction, that they might ingroſs all. And though at that time it might be thought fit to let it paſs ſo, rather than hazard the loſs of the Bill; yet now that we have a Prince whom we may ſafely truſt, and great Reaſon to unite our whole ſtrength againſt the common Enemy, not to remove that Obſtacle by ſo eaſie an Expedient, as inſtead of <hi>according to the uſage of the Church of England, in ſome Publick Church,</hi> to make it <hi>in ſome ſolemn or Publick Aſſembly of Proteſtants,</hi> and the Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificates to be by the Perſons who adminiſter, and three or four credible Perſons of the Aſſembly, or ſomething to the like effect; may be thought in them who oppoſe it, an argument of greater affection to the late King <hi>James,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:100584:15"/>than to the preſent King <hi>William,</hi> and to the Papiſts or the Faction, than to the true Proteſtant Intereſt, ſince ſuch an alteration doth not in the leaſt impede the deſign of the Act ſo fully as before declared.</p>
            <p>Another is, That we do not intangle our ſelves in our own Policies, by ſtooping to little Arts and pieces of vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Craft, but proceeding ſteadily upon Principles of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Humanity, and true Wiſdom, unneceſſarily exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate none, give all fair and reaſonable Terms, Conditions and Benefits that can be deſir'd to all; but never expoſe a good Cauſe by ſo mean Compliance, as to commit matters of great Truſt and weight to ſuch as are not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely for it, but whoſe declared Principles make ſuch a Condeſcention as little honourable as ſafe. To be plain, the People of this Nation being divided in Opinion upon the late Revolution, part holding that the Right of the late King <hi>James,</hi> by his own Actions, and the Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereupon of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> by their Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives fairly choſen, is fully determined, and that the Royal Authority is juſtly and effectually, to all intents and purpoſes transferred to the preſent King and Queen; but others being of opinion that King <hi>James</hi> is ſtill King <hi>de Jure,</hi> and King <hi>William</hi> only King <hi>de Facto:</hi> Theſe laſt are again divided among themſelves into two or three parties; one part being ſatisfied to live peaceably and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly under the preſent Government, but not to ſwear Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to the preſent King, nor act under him againſt the former; another part being zealous for the reſtoring of King <hi>James:</hi> And a third of ſuch, who though they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their Opinion, that King <hi>James</hi> is ſtill King <hi>de Jure,</hi> yet make no ſcruple to act under the preſent King, not only in little matters, but in ſuch matters of State and War, wherein they muſt either act directly againſt him, whom they acknowledge to have the Right, or elſe be falſe to him who entruſts 'em. And this is the Party that I mean: whom becauſe I cannot ſee how in Conſcience
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100584:15"/>they can act as they do, I cannot ſee how in prudence they can be truſted. And therefore I ſhould think it no hard or unreaſonable matter to ſecure the Government againſt all the Dangers which may ariſe from Men of thoſe Principles; for if they may freely enjoy not only their own private Rights, but alſo all ſuch publick Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments and Preferments, as are confirment with their Principles for them to execute, which is as much as in Honeſty and Conſcience they can deſire, or in Honour and Prudence can be committed to them, they have no reaſon to complain, but reſt ſatisfied therewith, and thankful to God for his Deliverance from a worſe condition: and thoſe, who profeſſing theſe Principles are yet not ſatisfied with all that, may juſtly be ſuſpected as Perſons either of vain and ambitious minds, or of turbulent and ill Deſigns, and therefore not to be admitted to any publick Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at all, or to be diſcharged if already in any ſuch. For theſe are the Men whom I apprehend to have been the moſt effectual Remora's in our Proceedings, and chief Occaſions, or Inſtruments in all our Diſappointments.</p>
            <p>And indeed I have all along from the beginning look'd upon a certain Condeſcention to a Compliance with ſome of this Party, to be <hi>one of the firſt falſe Steps</hi> which have been made ſince the beginning of the Revolution; and a <hi>Daubing,</hi> into which we were Betrayed by the pedantick Policies of ſome, who had ſpecial reaſon to have made better uſe of a good Caution againſt it; a thing of ſo pernicious Conſequence to his Majeſty, that I look upon the Miſcarriage of <hi>Torrington</hi> to be but a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle in compariſon to it, and as inconſiſtent with true Divinity, as with true Policy. Poor Prince! how did my Heart ake for him about that time, though I knew not what was the matter. But Princes are Men, and ſubject to the like Infirmities with other Men; and to ſuch Overſights as bring many times much Trouble and Diſturbance after them. But what <hi>Error in Divinity</hi> was
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100584:16"/>here committed, I will leave to the Conſideration of thoſe, whoſe Office it was to have diſcerned and given faithful Notice of it, rather than prove a Temptation, and miſlead into it; though I doubt the fault here in this will be as little underſtood, as was that in the Order of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for the Thankſgiving by the Vindicator. For when Mens Minds are much intended to the things of the World, and bigg with the acqueſt of them, they are uſually thereby too much diverted and clouded to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, and be of quick Underſtanding in ſuch matters, be the importance thereof what it will: But for <hi>the Error in Policy,</hi> ſince we feel ſo much of it, I think it greatly concerns the King and Kingdom, that it be well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, and ſpeedily redreſſed. By that one Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention which I mention'd before, was much of that great Authority, and true Majeſty, which the ſpecial Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God had conferr'd upon his Inſtrument, and was really a Talent to be wiſely uſed, unhappily loſt and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to a Party not entire for his Intereſt: For thereby was the whole Party, whereof many were doubtful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, greatly confirmed, and animated, and raiſed above their Expectations and themſelves. Nor was this all: for this made others, who were not otherwiſe of the Party, ſeeing the Stream run ſo ſtrong that way, preſently fall in with them: So that their numbers were thereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by the concurrence of many, who regarding only which ſide was moſt prevalent, would as readily have joyned with thoſe, who being fully ſatisfied with the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Cauſe, and of the Proceedings, were cordial and entire Friends to it, had they appeared as powerful in Favour at the Court. And this, as it made them appear more conſiderable to others, ſo that, when they obſerv'd it made them ſtill more confident to promote ſuch Perſons and Things, as, if throughly examined, will be found to have been more for the Service of the late King <hi>James,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King, than of the preſent King, and the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100584:16"/>Not only ſuch, as were heretofore Creatures of the late King, but ſuch as few thought well affected to this, and are believed to have really done no little Service to the former, and Diſſervice to this, by unfaithful Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, have been firſt recommended, and afterward ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, even from the effectual Proceedings of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelf. And this again hath produced <hi>another</hi> miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Conſequence, that generally ſuch as depend upon their Employments, obſerving how all Miſcarriages are covered, and either wholly vindicated, or greatly extenuated, and the Agents protected and ſecured, they dare not ſpeak out what they know, for fear of diſobliging not only this powerful Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but even the Criminals themſelves. And as foul and groſs a Miſcarriage as this hath been of the late Admiral at Sea, it is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally believed by ſuch as converſe much with Seamen, that many are afraid to diſoblige him if they ſhould ſpeak out. In theſe Obſervations I might proceed <hi>one ſtep further;</hi> but I think fit to ſtop here, this being ſufficient to demonſtrate to any man of ſenſe, in how dangerous a Condition the King and Queen are, of being delivered up as an Expiatory Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to their Enemies, and theſe Nations of being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved in Blood and Confuſion; and from whence all this Danger comes. And though <hi>other Inſtances</hi> might be given of ſuch Counſels and Proceedings as were of dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Conſequence, and miſchievous to the King and his Intereſt; yet I deſire not to exaſperate or aggravate things unneceſſarily, this which I have ſaid being alone ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to evince the Error of that Policy, from which all hath proceeded.</p>
            <p>It makes me many times think of the Subtile Policies of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, who thought by his King-craft to have out-done all the World, but was in moſt matters of moment over-reached himſelf. Juſt ſuch hath proved this daubing Policy of ſome conceited Politicians, impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of delay in ſome expected Preferments, who unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily miſlead the King at his firſt coming into ſo dangerous
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100584:17"/>and unſafe a Tract, and being better skilled in the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of vulgar Policy, than in the Practice of that which is ſolid and ſubſtantial, by over-doing have undone all, and built upon ſo falſe and ſandy a Foundation, as will bring all into Confuſion, unleſs it be ſpeedily prevented by ſome very good and effectual Means. For otherwiſe as we have been betrayed all along, we are like ſtill ſo to be, till both King and Kingdom be ſurpriz'd and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd in ſome ſuch Miſchiefs as aforeſaid. This, it is plain to all, who have Wit enough to perceive it, and Honeſty enough to confeſs it, was very near to have been our Caſe this Summer, had not the ſpecial Providence of God interpos'd and prevented it, by preſerving both the Kings Perſon, and our Fleet, from the neareſt approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of Deſtruction that could be. A Deliverance, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, if well underſtood, and conſidered in all its Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, not inferiour to thoſe of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and <hi>Gun-Powder</hi> Treaſon. And I wiſh we may be wiſe, ſtrengthen our ſelves indeed, and mark and ſee what we do: for at the Return of the Year, thoſe <hi>Syrians,</hi> if they find ſtill ſuch Encouragement from home, will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly again come up againſt us.</p>
            <p>But what are theſe <hi>Good and Effectual Means,</hi> by which all this Miſchief may be prevented? Why, that alſo I will endeavour by the Grace of God to declare plainly. And the plain truth is, it is meer Brutiſhneſs and Stupidity not to look further than all this, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a <hi>Precedent</hi> effectual <hi>Cauſe,</hi> to which a proper appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation muſt be made, before any Relief or Amendment can be had; and which, till that be done, will rankle, feſter, and produce ſtill worſe ſymptoms upon the uſe of whatever other Means we can think of. For all this is of God, who hath the Hearts of all Men in his Hand, and hath done admirably in all theſe things, hath cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected us but in mercy, and given us fair warning. He preſerved our Fleet from ſurprize and ſudden Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100584:17"/>when at anchor in St. <hi>Hellens</hi> Bay, the <hi>French</hi> were ſo near as <hi>Freſh-water</hi> Bay before they knew it: And he preſerved the King's Perſon, when he yet ſuffered a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Bullet to come ſo very near as to touch him. He gave him a very Glorious Victory at Land, and yet again ſo ordered it, that he ſhould ſuffer a great Dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution of all that Glory, by a baffle of his Fleet at Sea, and of his Army at Land againſt <hi>Lymerick;</hi> whereas he could eaſily have prevented both if he had pleaſed; I wiſh both King and People may lay theſe things to Heart, and conſider wiſely what is fit to be done, leaſt the next Buliet may be permitted, inſtead of the Skin to take the Heart, and the next Engagement inſtead of Baf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, bring Confuſion upon the Nation: It is dangerous dallying in this Caſe, and dangerous trifling in Sacred Things. I will not repeat what I have ſaid before in my Reflections upon the Occurrences of the laſt Year; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I need not, for I have too much new Matter to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Nor does it belong to me to enquire what hath been done in purſuance of the King's Pious and Prudent Letter to the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and the other Biſhops; for that belongs to them to do. But this I will ſay, though it make the Ears of all pious People that hear it to tingle, if by any means I may raiſe up a better Spirit in the Nation, and ſhame the great Men of it into better Manners in time, to prevent a more ſevere Correction. I had a Meſſage ſent me by a very Pious and Reverend Divine of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> That it was deſired by divers of the Biſhops, that I would prepare a Bill for them for an Act of Parliament, for more effectual correcting of the notorious Sins and Vices of this Nation. Who thoſe Biſhops were, I was not told, nor was it material; but I could not but readily embrace ſo pious a Motion, and therefore preſently ſet to work, drew up a foul Draught, and adviſed firſt with ſome private Friends of good Ability, and at laſt with divers of the Judges, who were then in Town, about it. The Sins and Vices were the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100584:18"/>ſame which were expreſs'd in that good Letter before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned of the King to the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and the Pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble moſt of it in the words, and to the effect of that Letter; and the Puniſhments ſuch as are warranted by the Laws of God and Man; and being fair tranſcribed it was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to a very good Biſhop, who was ſpoken to by the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> to Preach before the Lords the Faſt-Day before <hi>Eaſter:</hi> The good Man laboured with much Zeal to promote it, and intended to have recommended it to their Lordſhips at their Houſe, before they went to Church, as the moſt proper time that could be; but the Lords nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther met at their Houſe, nor came to the <hi>Abby</hi> Church, as is uſual upon ſuch Occaſions, in a Body (though an Omiſſion apt to be imputed to want of Devotion to God in ſome, and of Affection to the Cauſe in others;) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being diſappointed in that, the next time they met he acquainted them with the Bill, and deſired Leave to bring it into the Houſe, which was granted indeed, but the Motion ſo entertain'd by ſome, that the moſt Prudential of our Biſhops adviſed not to venture the reading of it till a more favourable time, leaſt it ſhould be rejected; and their Authority kept it out at that time, and I doubt will be apt to do the like at any other, unleſs this plain dealing can help it, and therefore I think fit to conſider this Matter a little further.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Firſt,</hi> here is matter of very ſerious and ſad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, that Vice and Wickedneſs ſhould be ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent among the Nobility of this Nation, that the whole Body of the Biſhops of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhould not dare to offer to bring in a Bill for the Reformation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, leaſt it ſhould be rejected. And if our Nobility be come to that Degree of Obſtinacy and Impudence in Sin and Wickedneſs, and Infatuation and Folly, as to outface the Gravity and Authority of our Biſhops, and that not ſeverally, but when aſſembled together, and in ſo ſolemn an Aſſembly, what good can we expect from them; but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100584:18"/>rather that they ſhould provoke the Judgments of God upon themſelves and the whole Nation, for the Chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that which doth ſo outface all Humane Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is matter of as ſerious and ſad Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Biſhops of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhould be ſunk ſo low in their Authority, be become ſo mean in that Eſteem and Veneration with the People, which uſed to be paid to Perſons in that Sacred Function, and ſhould retain ſo little of true Chriſtian Generoſity and Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, as that the whole Body of them in ſuch an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſhould not be able by their Gravity and weighty Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions to awe and confound the Malapertneſs of a few inconſiderate Noblemen, if any ſuch ſhould appear, though with the concurrence of divers of the Temporal Lords, which doubtleſs would not be wanting; and in caſe the leading Men among them did diſlike that Bill or any thing in it, that they who diſlike it, ſhould have ſo little Zeal for the Honour and Service of God, the good of this Church and Nation, and the Reputation of their own Order, as not of themſelves to provide a better before this time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And this opens a very ſad, but uſeful and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Proſpect to all the ſincere and ſerious Friends of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> whereby we may come to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtanding both of our own Communion, and of the Diſſenters; and of our Behaviour toward them, what it hath been, and what it ought to be. For our own Communion, we ſee here that which may correct and humble us for our vain magnifying of our Church above all others, and our deſpiſing; villifying and diſturbing our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who are in many reſpects better than our ſelves; and how properly applicable that Admonition of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Witneſs to the Church of the <hi>Laodiceans</hi> is to us, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Thou ſayeſt I am rich, and increaſed with goods, and have need of nothing; and knoweſt not that thou art wretched, and miſerable, and poor, and blind, and naked:</hi> And
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100584:19"/>what reaſon we have to fear leaſt that Judgment denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt them, be inflicted upon us, who are ſo little behind them in the ſame fault: <hi>Becauſe thou art lukewarm, and neither cold nor hot, I will ſpew thee out:</hi> For here we ſee the chief of our Clergy and the chief of our Laity in one of our moſt ſolemn Civil Aſſemblies; and if we look into thoſe which ſhould be Sacred Aſſemblies, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny but that they are generally greatly prophaned: For all theſe Perſons, of whom our whole Body of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops are ſo afraid, are all Members of our Church; not only admitted into it by Baptiſm, but freely admitted to the moſt ſacred Rites in it. And as much overſpread with Vice, Prophaneneſs and Debauchery as this Nation is, all is receiv'd with a full torrent into our Church: So that there is ſcarce a notorious ſcandalous Perſon in the whole Nation, but is of our Communion; and if he be a Perſon of Quality, and Zealous for the Church, Complemented and Treated even by our Biſhops themſelves. Such <hi>is the Diſcipline</hi> of our Church, the end of which among the ancient Chriſtians was to preſerve the Honour and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of our Holy Profeſſion; but ſo little of that have we remaining among us, that that Popiſh Relique which we have of Diſcipline, doth rather increaſe, what the genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine Chriſtian Diſcipline would cure.</p>
            <p>We are guilty of a like neglect <hi>in our Worſhip;</hi> only it is not peculiar to us, but common to all the Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is very defective in that reſpect. Nor is there any Excuſe for us, that I know of, but Ignorance, which is ſhameful enough among Men pretending ſo much to Learning: But if we can but purchaſe a little more Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Modeſty, and Condeſcention to the Infirmities of our Brethren, by it, it will be well. I do not know of any Church in the World, from the Paſſion of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to the time of the Reformation, where the Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that bleſſed Sacrament of the Euchariſt, was not a part (as it is the peculiar part of the Chriſtian Worſhip)
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100584:19"/>of their ordinary publick Worſhip of God, inſomuch that it was commonly called <hi>Sacrificium quotidianum</hi> their daily Sacrifice: The Principal Uſes of it are: 1. A ſolemn Act of Recognition of our Redemption, and of the Dominion of our Saviour thereby acquired over us. 2. A Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Paſſion of our Saviour to God the Father in our ſolemn Aſſemblies, as effectual to all intents and purpoſes in the Churches of the Gentiles, as were any or all the Sacrifices of the Jews under the Law. 3. A Spiritual Communion between God and the Souls of the Faithful, as real as was that between our Saviour and the faithful Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who touch'd his Garment, when he felt Vertue go out of him. 4. A Sacred Communion and Confederation between the Faithful themſelves: And where all this is neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, what can it be imputed to, but either want of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion and of a grateful Senſe of our Redemption, and a ſupine Neglect of our own greateſt Concern; or Infidelity and Ignorance, which, as I ſaid, is the beſt, though ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſhameful, excuſe we can make? In the Greek Church where this Neglect firſt began, as is noted by St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and much complain'd of by <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> it was follow'd with diſmal Contentions, Diviſions and Confuſions: And I am of opinion, that not only the great Decay of Chriſtian Piety, but the unhappy Diviſions of our Church, may be imputed to this Neglect among us, as one principal Cauſe. And I am well ſatisfied that our want of a daily Chriſtian Sacrifice among us is one of the principal Prejudices, which hinder the Reconciliation of the beſt of the Engliſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts to us; which would be much more eaſie, if that and two or three more Points of Controverſie were but a little better look'd into and ſetled. But our <hi>Second Service,</hi> as we uſe it, with no little inconvenience in many Churches, is <hi>peculiar to us,</hi> a Novelty, ſuch as was once introduced in <hi>France,</hi> and called <hi>Miſſa ſicca,</hi> and <hi>Miſſa nautica,</hi> but ſoon exploded as a jejune and barren thing; and bears witneſs againſt us for our neglect of that, without which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100584:20"/>our Liturgy or Service in the Judgment of Learned Men, and of Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> in particular, is imperfect. Beſides, our Offices and Collects are defective, and not ſufficient for all occaſions (as may be perceived by the Bills which are daily put up to the Readers) or to expreſs the Devotion of many pious Souls in the ordinary Service.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Doctrin of the Church of England</hi> declared in our Articles, it is certain that moſt of the Diſſenters are as much for it as thoſe of our Communion, and more than divers of them are; and therefore I need ſay nothing of that. But much of the Doctrin which hath been taught too often in our Churches ſince the Return of King <hi>Charles the Second,</hi> with a great deal of confidence, hath been ſo far from the genuine Chriſtian Doctrin, that it tends very much to the Subverſion thereof; to divert People from the Life and Power of Religion by reproachful Imputation of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticiſm and Enthuſiaſm; from the ſtrict conſciencious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of it by the like reproachful terms of Bigottry and Presbyterianiſm; and to introduce inſtead of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Life and Heavenly Converſation of genuine Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, a kind of ſuperficial Formality and Phariſaical Morality, abſtaining indeed from groſs, ſcandalous Sins, which any Man of ſenſe would do for his own Reputation; but leaving the Soul as much immerſed in terrene Affections, as if thoſe emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Vertues of Humility, Contempt of the Word, Heavenly-mindedneſs, Devotion to God and univerſal Charity to all ſort of Men, ſo much ſtudied and practiſed by the Ancient Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, were things rather to be pitied in them as weakneſs, or unneceſſary trouble, or Superſtition, than imitated by us.</p>
            <p>Of our Clergy, I thank God, we have many of good Learning, Vertue and Piety; Men of Moderation and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to all Men, but eſpecially to all ſerious and pious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, though of different opinions concerning many things diſputed in matters of Religion; and well content they ſhould quietly enjoy the freedom of their Religion, and Civil Rights, and ſerve their Country, and be admitted
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100584:20"/>into the Communion and Service of our Church upon as eaſie terms as may be. But there are again, no ſmall part who are groſly ſcandalous, or, if not ſo groſly ſcandalous, yet make a Trade of Divinity, apply themſelves to it as others do to Trades and Civil Profeſſions, to get their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, Eſtates and Preferments by it; preach indeed and read Prayers, if they cannot keep Curates; but have little care more of the Souls committed to their charge, and therefore never ſcruple at any charge though never ſo great, ſo the Profits to their Purſe be but great; and though not ſo groſly ſcandalous, give great offence to People of the higher Ranks and Parts, by their eager and inſatiable purſuit of Preferments; and thereby tempt them to ſuſpect that they believe not themſelves the Doctrin which they preach, as I was not long ſince upon ſuch an occaſion told by a Perſon of great place and parts, that he thought them all Atheiſts; which though, I ſuppoſe, more than he did indeed believe, yet ſhews how apt it is to tempt Men to it, and I doubt not but prevails with ſome: And however that be, it is certainly ſo great a temptation and incentive to Worldly-mindedneſs, Covetouſneſs, Pride and Ambition, that it utterly diſables them to preach with any Life and Succeſs, againſt thoſe Vices and Sins, which though not ſo ſcandalous in vulgar Reputation as ſome others, are not leſs enſnaring to Souls and pernicious to States and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Societies. And indeed a great part of our Clergy are plainly infected and overſpread with Formality and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiſm, almoſt in all the inſtances of it except the beſt, that is, Zeal for making Proſelites. But as to that, I doubt the whole Church of <hi>England</hi> hath much to anſwer for before God, who hath left them deſtitute of no Means or Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to propagate the Goſpel to the remoteſt parts of the World, yet have they not all equalled what hath been done by one ſingle Gentleman, a Lay-man. Nay, even at home; neither in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> or <hi>Ireland</hi> is the Goſpel yet ſo throughly planted, but that vaſt Fields may be truly ſaid
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100584:21"/>to lie ſtill uncultivated. And if we enter a little farther we ſhall ſee yet greater Abominations than theſe, even in this great and populous City: What great numbers of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have we, who have either no Pariſh-Churches to repair to, or not capacious enough to receive them? and what numbers of Clergy-men walking about the Streets ſeeking for Employment? and ſome to my knowledge in great ſtraits and neceſſities; (I could ſay more, but I forbear) while the Fat of the Land is ingroſſed and devoured by others; ill Husbandmen certainly, who will not provide Labourers, becauſe they are not willing to pay their Wages. But what doth our Church in this caſe? Why are not ſuch Perſons as will undertake great Charges, more than one, or two, or more can ſufficiently diſcharge, for the ſake of great Revenues, admoniſhed of their Duty, what in Conſcience they ought to do, by our Biſhops in their Viſitations? Are they only the Canons of the Church, and the Laws of the Land that the Biſhops of our Church are to act by? Are the Admonitions of our Biſhops in Matters of Duty and Conſcience of ſo little Authority with our own Clergy, unleſs we have Canon or Statute to compel Conformity? And in caſe the Revenues of ſuch a place be not ſufficient to maintain Labourers enough, where is the Piety and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of our dignified Clergy, and the Uſe of our ample Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues in our Church, that we have no Evangeliſts ſent out and maintained at the charge of the Church to ſupply theſe and the like occaſions? And where we ſee ſo little Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the Souls of Men, what wonder is it if their Piety and Devotion to God be proportionable? If they invite not others to the daily worſhip of God in publick, when we ſee it ſo rarely frequented by themſelves? Nay not uſed in many Churches but Sundays; or Sundays, Wedneſs days and Fridays; or not at ſuch hours as ſome of their charge, and ſuch as they ought to have a ſpecial care of-can only have for that ſervice, without they will be at the charge themſelves to hire a Reader on purpoſe? and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>haps
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100584:21"/>not ſo much as that permitted without much entreaty nor injoyed without diſturbance ſometimes? as if Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were all their work, and Hearing all that is neceſſary for the People; or common Civility all their Religion; but daily preſenting our ſelves before God to worſhip him in publick, and aſſembling our ſelves together in ſuch holy Worſhip, to animate one another thereunto, and beget and confirm mutual Charity and Piety, was not part of that Practice, which is the very End of Preaching and Hearing. And what wonder if ſuch inſtruct not as they ought, and preſs not their People to frequent the moſt ſolemn and peculiar part of our Chriſtian Worſhip, and then to excuſe their own neglect falſly accuſe their People, and charge it upon them?</p>
            <p>More I might ſay, but I need ſay no more, nor have I ſaid ſo much with any ill mind, but beſides other good Ends for the real Service of this Church, and the good of thoſe, who perhaps will ſome of them be offended at it, if there be any ſo void of Piety and Conſideration: That we may better know our ſelves, and be humbled for what we really are, and not vainly vaunt of what we are not: That find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves ſo faulty, we may learn more Moderation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Brethren; leſt by too ſeverely judging them, inſtead of judging our ſelves as we ought, we provoke the Judgment of God upon us; eſpecially when we our ſelves give the occaſions of what we quarrel with them for, by a Phriſaical Exaction of things not neceſſary, inſtead of Chriſtian Condeſcention to the Infirmities of the weak; by Phariſaical Perſecution of Nonconformity to the Orders of Men, and at the ſame time permitting notorious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Laws of God by our own Members without check or controle, or ſcarce ſerious reſentment; by driving them by our Prophanation and want of Diſciplin from our Aſſemblies, and yet like Madmen labouring by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural means of Force to compel them thereunto: (A Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticiſm indeed, juſtly to be charged upon many, who falſly charge it upon others) For it is a truth too notorious to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100584:22"/>be deny'd, that we have few Chriſtian Aſſemblies, but thoſe of the Diſſenters, which can properly be called <hi>Holy;</hi> being generally all profaned by ſcandalous Members, and moſt of all thoſe of our Chathedrals, even by ſcandalous Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who officiate in the Choirs, the exerciſe of our Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline not extending ſo far as to the Reformation of them who are ſo near at home. Laſtly, that all ſerious, pious, vertuous and conſiderate Men, who are true Lovers of their Country, may have a right Information concerning theſe things; and ſeeing deeper into this Myſtery of Iniquity, may no longer ſuffer themſelves to be abus'd and made Tools to ſupport a pernicious Faction of Men, who for their own worldly advantage cry aloud for the Church, as if it was in danger by others, when they themſelves do moſt of all endanger it, by the Animoſities, whereby they divide it, and the Formality and Prophanation, whereby it is expoſed, to the great offence of many ſerious and pious People; but as becomes wiſe Men and underſtanding Chriſtians, taking theſe things into ſerious conſideration, apply our ſelves in good ſober ſadneſs to the proper means to preſerve both Church and State, that is, to prevent the Judgments of God, which are otherwiſe like to overturn both by a ſpeedy and ſubſtantial Reformation, by ſincerly ſeeking a Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with our Brethren, whom we have offended by our Scandals and harſh and uncharitable dealings, and all unite as fellow Chriſtians and Compatriots, and joyn all our ſtrength and forces firſt to ſuppreſs and exterminate the Common Enemy at home, our reigning Sins of Prophaneſs, Debauchery and Contempt of the Goſpel, and then ſelect the moſt proper, the moſt faithful and beſt qualified, for Council, Conduct, Induſtry and Courage, of what ever Rank, Degree or Profeſſion they be, if ſober and vertuous, to employ both for management at home, and againſt our Enemies abroad. Then may we hope to proſper, but not till then: For as the Miſcarriages of Princes often bring Miſchiefs upon the People, ſo do the Sins and Wickedneſs of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100584:22"/>the People as often bring Croſſes and Diſappointments upon the moſt hopeful Enterprizes of the beſt of Princes; not only as natural Conſequences, but by the ſpecial Judgments of God. And this brings me to my next Obſervation upon that buſineſs of the Bill. And therefore,</p>
            <p>Fourthly, This <hi>Prudential Advice,</hi> which prevailed to lay aſide that Bill till a more favourable time, may ſatifie us of the truth of what I mentioned in my former Reflections modeſtly, and only as matter of ſuſpicion, <hi>viz.</hi> That the King had not been faithfully dealt with in a matter of the ſame nature, and of great moment to himſelf, in reſpect of a ſpecial Duty incumbent upon him by a ſpecial Obligation, as well as to the Nation. For as we ſee plainly that the ſame Prudential Conſiderations prevailed in both, ſo there is no reaſon to doubt but they came from the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; and if my Information fails me not, theſe were not the only times they did ſo. I am ſorry that this vain Worldly Wiſdom, which is Fooliſhneſs with God, ſhould be ſo deeply imbibed by ſuch as ſhould underſtand better things, and I doubt will one day be call'd to account for it. But I do not a little rejoyce to ſee that ſo plainly, which I hope may mitigate much of the Offence in the King though it light ſo much the heavier ſomewhere elſe. For I am ſo well ſatisfied that neither of theſe Prudential Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, which I have mention'd, are conſiſtent either with true Policy or ſound Divinity, or free from ſuch Sin, as doth uſually provoke at leaſt ſmart Corrections, that I dare undertake to make it good againſt the Author or Authors of them, whoever he or they are. But as this is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place to add more to what I have ſaid already on that Subject; ſo I hope the fair Admonitions, which our own Experience hath already given us, will make it needleſs. And therefore without further Reflections upon what is paſt, we are now to look forward what is now to be done, and what are thoſe <hi>Good and Effectual Means</hi> to ſet us free from this impedited and enchanted Condition.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:100584:23"/>
            <p>And the firſt thing to be done is to lay a good Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſecure the Favour and Bleſſing of the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; which alone can make all go on proſperous and ſmooth, and very ſuccesful; but without it, all other, the moſt proper means that can be propos'd, will ſtill prove ineffectual and abortive, and be retarded with perpetual croſs Accidents and Diſappointments; nay prove themſelves occaſions of Miſchief. And this in truth has been our Caſe, whether it has been underſtood or not, from our firſt At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of reducing <hi>Ireland.</hi> Miſcarriages in Perſons im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed and intruſted I eaſily allow to be the immediate Cauſes: But 'tis a ſuperficial Inſpection that can ſee no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the Matter: The Original Cauſe lies a ſtep or two farther back; but we are here only to look forward: Therefore in ſhort, the only true way, to obtain or ſecure the Favour and Bleſſing of God, is to remove the <hi>Curſed Thing</hi> which hath all this while interpoſed and with-held them from us. And it muſt be begun by a ſpeedy, reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and effectual Reformation of the great Impiety and Wickedneſs of the Nation; and this muſt be begun by the King himſelf, and in another manner than is yet done. His Letter to the Biſhops is a good and pious Letter; but what good it hath done I know not. The Biſhops I know, talked of other Letters alſo of their own; but I ſee them not, or any good Effect of either. But the King hath a Civil Power, which muſt be exerted. It is his Office and Duty, <hi>To ſee the Laws duly executed;</hi> and when he finds that neglected, to ſend out his ſpecial Command to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire and enjoin the due Execution of them; and to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh or diſplace ſuch as are Negligent and Remiſs, and put others in their places, who will more faithfully diſcharge their Duty. It is his Duty alſo to <hi>recommend to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to make further Proviſion for ſuch Laws as he finds wanting to ſupply the Defects of thoſe we have already: And 'tis likewiſe His Duty, as well as His Wiſdom <hi>to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Vertue and Piety, and diſcountenance Vice and Wickedneſs,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:100584:23"/>by the diſpenſation of his Favours, and demonſtration of his Diſpleaſure accordingly. All this is moſt certainly his Duty, and if he doth not faithfully diſcharge it both to God and to the Nation, he cannot expect either the Bleſſing of God or the faithful Concurrence of the People with him. But becauſe I find no reaſon to doubt of his own good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations to ſo good a Work, I ſee but two things fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary to be noted to this Purpoſe: The one, that he beware of, and baniſh from his Preſence ſuch Perſons, eſpecially Clergy-men, as he hath found, either evil Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors or falſe Guides, in a Matter of ſo apparent Duty and great Importance to himſelf and the Nation. The other, that he likewiſe beware, (and to that purpoſe give encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to faithful Informations) that he partake not in the ſins of the late Kings, by ſetting up notorious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Vice and Wickedneſs in Honour or great Places. And upon this Occaſion I cannot but take Notice of what I have been told, by one who ſaid he was preſent, that two of the Principal Officers of our Fleet, (whom he Named) before the late Engagement, when they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Sacrament to qualifie them for their Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, entertained themſelves at Dinner with pleaſant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of what Women and whoſe Wives they had De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd: And it is reported that a Perſon notorious over all <hi>England</hi> for the like Injury, with ſome aggravation to a Perſon of Quality, is lately put into a great Place in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Such impious Perſons, who glory in their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety and Contempt of Religion, ought to be abominated and deteſted by all Men, as Enemies of God and Men, and Aſſociates of Devils and Curſed damned Spirits. Shall a mortal Man be moved at an Affront or Contempt offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his Father or his Friend, thô abſent; and ſhall not all Men (even the <hi>Mob,</hi> as we call them, who have more Steddineſs, Conſtancy and Virtue, than a great part of our Nobility and Gentry have had of late) expreſs their Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt thoſe, who ſhall dare thus to Contemn and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100584:24"/>Affront the great and glorious Author of our Being, upon whom we all continually depend, by ſuch impudent Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of his righteous Laws? Be they Gentlemen or No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-men, or what they will, they are ten thouſand times worſe than the Dirt of the Streets, and ought to be trod upon by the meaneſt of Humane Race. Nay, ſhall a King, who is but a mortal Worm, expect Honour and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Fidelity from his Fellow-Creatures, and many of them poſſibly upon a true eſtimate much better than Himſelf; and yet endure the Majeſty of Heaven, whoſe Deputy he is, to be ſo affronted, by thoſe whom his Divine Providence hath ſubjected to his Power to be govern'd in all Righteouſneſs, and not exert the utmoſt of that Power, and uſe all means poſſible to ſuppreſs them, thô it were to the hazard of twenty Kingdoms, and a thouſand Lives beſides? Certainly Humane Nature, were it not mightily corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, could not with any Patience endure ſuch Contempt of our Creator and Redeemer, and the Religion we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs. And beſides all this, what good can we expect with any Moral Aſſurance from People of ſo little Conſideration and Conſtancy, or Command of themſelves, as to hazard their Souls, by proſtituting Religion to give Credentials to a vitious Prince, that they might more eaſily obtain his Favour; or of ſo little Wit and Obſervation, as no better to diſtinguiſh Times and Perſons, but think this King muſt needs be ſuch as themſelves are, or the former, that they impudently perſiſt in the ſame wicked Courſes, and take this Liberty to affront Religion, which he profeſſeth, not in ſhew as the other did, but in reality? And therefore to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Matter, as it is the Kings Duty to remove ſuch Abuſes and ſcandalous Perſons, it being in his Power of himſelf to do it, ſo it is the Right of the Subject, and their Duty too to God, to deſire and demand it. For we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect the Bleſſing of God to be with us, 'till thoſe Scandals and Abominations be removed, either by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation or Removal of the Perſons, or by the Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100584:24"/>of moſt of them in a long continued War, without Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the King, or Satisfaction to the People, 'till that be done. And I may be bold to ſay, it is deſir'd and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of him, by all the Serious, Virtuous and Pious, (that is, the beſt, and which will prove in concluſion the moſt prevalent Part) of the Nation. Chriſtianity will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly revive here in a ſhort time in its ancient Power and Splendor; and nothing can be ſo glorious and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to this King as to be a vigorous Inſtrument in it.</p>
            <p>This Foundation being well laid, we may proceed to the reſt with Confidence of the Divine Favour and Bleſſing upon us, and that no Oppoſition ſhall be able to ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us: And <hi>the next Buſineſs</hi> will be, <hi>to put the Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Affairs into the hands of ſuch as the King may reaſonably Confide in,</hi> for their Integrity and Affection to his Cauſe, and ſufficient Qualifications for the Imployments committed to them. And this is a Duty which the King owes both to the Kingdom, and to his Confederates in this great Cauſe, and he cannot in Honour, no more than in Prudence do otherwiſe. Nay, I will ſay more, it is a Duty, which he owes to God, whoſe Cauſe it is, who hath raiſed him up to be his Inſtrument in it, who hath given him ſo great Experiments of his Conduct and Protection, and is ſtill ready to proſper him in it, provided he be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to his Conduct, and do not diſhonour him by relaxing his Confidence therein, and yielding to the Temptation of vulgar Politicks; which would but weaken his Intereſt, and prove deceitful and a Snare to him. <hi>Fidelity of Soul</hi> to God is the great buſineſs and exerciſe of all our Lives; but in them who are raiſed up to be Inſtruments in any great Work, it is in a ſpecial manner required that it be firm and ſteddy, as becomes thoſe who are experienc'd Maſters in it, not mutable and unſtable like Novices and Learners. To this is required great Courage and Vigour, grounded upon firm Truſt and Confidence in the infallible Wiſdom and Power of God, with an intire reſignation of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100584:25"/>the Event of all to his Will: But there is alſo required true Wiſdom to improve all Opportunities and Advantages, and to avoid all Inconveniences, and truly to diſtinguiſh which are which. And there is moreover required Righteouſneſs, without which there can be neither true Wiſdom, whatever ſpecious appearance it may have, nor Fidelity to God; for it would be a departure from his Ways, and a Diſtruſt of the ſufficiency of his Conduct, and a Diſhonour to him. And whoever ſteps out of his Way, will certainly intangle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and loſe all his labour at the leaſt. Such courſes ſhall never proſper, or bring a Man benefit, if they bring not greater Miſchief upon him. I ſpeak of his good Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for good, and not of his Inſtruments for Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Vengeance, ſuch as Evil Spirits, and Evil Men, whom he frequently lets looſe to ſatisfie their own wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Appetites for puniſhment of others. I have already diſtinguiſhed with relation to this buſineſs <hi>four ſorts of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> in this Nation; one part who are zealous for reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the late King <hi>James,</hi> and that theſe are not to be employ'd, I need not uſe many words to demonſtrate: but yet I think that they alſo are to be diſtinguiſh'd; and that ſuch of them as never ſubmitted to this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but appear fairly as Enemies, are to be treated no worſe than Enemies of War, and not as Traitors; but ſuch as appear and act in publick as Subjects, and yet ſhall be found in ſecret Conſpiracies againſt this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may juſtly be dealt with as Traytors. Only thus much Favour I ſhould be for ever for them; that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I doubt not but there have been many this Summer actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally engaged in, or privy to a moſt dangerous Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and that not only for their King <hi>James,</hi> but under that pretence with the <hi>French,</hi> who are Enemies to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; yet if they will confeſs how far they have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in any ſuch matter, and either give ſufficient aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to ſubmit and live peaceably for the future, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare themſelves, and depart the Kingdom, they ſhould be
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100584:25"/>free ſo to do: but they who will not, are to be looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as Traytors; and it is part of that Fidelity which the King owes both to God, and to the People, who entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with the Government, to cauſe diligent and ſtrict Enquiry to be made into it, leaſt we be involved in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Michiefs before the next Summer be over.</p>
            <p>Another ſort are ſuch, who from ſome miſtaken Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Government, which they had unthinkingly imbib'd, are perſwaded that the late King <hi>James</hi> hath ſtill a Right; but conſidering his Religion, and to whom he hath ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Conſcience for Information and Direction, and what Confuſions and Miſchiefs were thereby begun, and likely in time to have been brought upon theſe Nations, and our Confederates, are ſenſible of the Providence and Mercy of God, in ſending us ſuch a Deliverance; and therefore thô they will not fooliſhly and ungratefully reſiſt this gracious Providence of God, but are willing to enjoy it in quiet; yet think fit not to ſtain or ſtrain their Conſciences in acting againſt him, who they think hath a Right. And theſe in my apprehenſion are right honeſt Men, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all the Favours and Kindneſs they can in reaſon deſire: And I ſhall endeavour in a more proper Place to do them ſome Service, by ſhewing them their Error; but I have no more to ſay of them here, in relation to ſuch Employments as I ſpeak of, for like honeſt men they will not accept them.</p>
            <p>A third ſort are of thoſe, who have the ſame Opinion of the Right of King <hi>James,</hi> that the former have, and will not recognize the preſent King and Queen to be rightful King and Queen; yet make no ſcruple to ſwear Allegiance to them, to act under their Authority, and not only ſo, but to act in Council and War againſt him whom they believe to have the Right ſtill, and they know hath had not long ſince the Poſſeſſion alſo. I know very well that by our Laws what is done for or againſt a King <hi>de Facto,</hi> is equally juſtifiable or puniſhable, as if he was alſo King <hi>de
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100584:26"/>Jure;</hi> and good reaſon there may be for it, <hi>viz.</hi> That honeſt well-meaning People may not ſuffer for what they do in the ſincerity of their Hearts, believing it to be juſt and right, and, That the Peace of the Kingdom may not be diſturbed upon pretence of, or for the Right of a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſon, though King <hi>de Jure.</hi> But this juſt and reaſonable Law, cannot, I doubt, excuſe, <hi>in foro Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> ſuch as for private temporal reſpects, or unneceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly act againſt one whom they believe to have the Right, and to be King <hi>de Jure.</hi> All honeſt Conſcientious Men are very cautious, and not eaſily perſwaded to act in a doubtful Caſe, when without doubt they may lawfully ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain; and therefore they who are eaſily perſwaded to it upon a Proſpect of Preferment, may juſtly be ſuſpected: But they who in ſuch Caſe thruſt themſelves forward, may be concluded to be Men of little Conſcience, Honeſty or Honour: And therefore I am of Opinion that they, who believe in their Conſcience that the late King hath yet a right to Reign, and that King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> are only King and Queen <hi>de Facto,</hi> and therefore refuſe and oppoſe a Recognition of them to be rightfull King and Queen, cannot in Honour or Honeſty act in Council or War in this Caſe. And for the ſame reaſon I am alſo of Opinion, that neither can any Prince, who acts not as a private Man for his own Intereſt, but as a publick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for a whole Society of Men, and, as our preſent Caſe is, for the common Concern of divers other Princes and People, in Prudence or Honour commit any ſuch Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to any Perſon of that Opinion. For it is plainly to tempt him firſt to be falſe to his own Conſcience for the ſake of the Employment, and next to be falſe to him who employs him for the ſake of his Conſcience: For no Man can long act vigorouſly and ſteddily, <hi>reluctante Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> and the Conſideration that Right (that is, what he takes to be ſo) may one day take place, will be a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual check upon him for ever doing any conſiderable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100584:26"/>againſt it; and a continual Motive to hearken to any probable Overtures for it. And this Conſideration, that the King cannot in Honour commit any ſuch Employment to them, as things ſtand at preſent, ought to be another Motive to them to abſtain, even out of Reſpect to the King, if they have any for him; and if they have not, he hath the leſs reaſon to employ them: But otherwiſe I would not have them abridged of the leaſt benefit of the Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that their Hearts can in reaſon deſire.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſeveral ſorts of Perſons are moſt of them of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, Gentry, Clergy, or Citizens of ſome particular Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or Officers in our Fleet and Armies: But of all our Nobility, or however of our Gentry, Clergy and Citizens of the ſeveral Cities of the Nation, I hope the greateſt part by much, and our Yeomanry, and the great Body of the People, and the Sea-men, are beyond all diſpute ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally all, entire for the preſent Settlement and Right of the preſent King and Queen: And all theſe are alſo firm for the Proteſtant Religion, and for the Common Good of the Nation, and for the Common Cauſe of the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates. And therefore it is all the reaſon in the World that all theſe, that is, the King and Queen, the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the Common Good of the Nation, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cauſe of all the Confederates, ſhould have the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and United Aſſiſtance of them all. Nor can I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that any will oppoſe it but ſuch as are in truth, in the bottom, more hearty for a Party, than for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion; for a Faction, than for the common Good of the Nation; for King <hi>James,</hi> than for King <hi>William;</hi> or for the Corruptions and Abuſes of Popery, than for the Purity and Power of the true Religion; and for the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations, Incroachments and Tyranny of the <hi>French Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> than for the juſt and noble Cauſe of the Confederates. And if this be true that I ſay, and I be not greatly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, it will hence follow that the King himſelf is oblig'd in Prudence, in Juſtice and Honour to recommend the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100584:27"/>of all Impediments, by the Statutes of the two laſt Reigns, to the Parliament with all Earneſtneſs; and that he, being a Proteſtant Prince, hath great reaſon to reſent any Oppoſition that ſhall be made to ſo neceſſary a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; and to take Notice of the Perſons, and Places which ſend any of them, as ſuch as are ſtill ſo levened with Faction, that they do not diſcern that the great Heats and Animoſities which have long diſturbed this Nation, were principally occaſioned and heightened to ſerve the Intereſt of the Papiſts, or a miſchievous Faction. And ſince this Parliament was choſen before the Act of Pardon was paſs'd, and the Elections and Returns in many Corporations, (where were many Criminals,) were made with great Heat and Faction by ſuch as were concerned to ſave themſelves, and all the Intereſt they could make, (as appears in the many Petitions before the Committee of Elections) if this Parliament will not agree upon what is neceſſary for the Common Good, it may prove a good Expedient to diſſolve them and call another ſpeedily, which probably may be choſen more fairly and indifferently. And thus much I thought fit to add to what I had mention'd before on the ſame Subjects, becauſe they are matters of ſo great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern.</p>
            <p>And now as to <hi>the ſpecial Qualifications</hi> of the Perſons to be employed; this poor Nation hath been long in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pitiful Condition in this reſpect, while this, which ought principally to be regarded, hath apparently been leaſt and laſt of all ſought after: King <hi>Charles</hi> heartily favouring ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few, who would not either comply with him in his voluptuous Courſes and Luxury, or ſerve him either in his Illegal Projects and Deſigns, or in abuſing the Nation out of their Money; and King <hi>James</hi> as few, who would not one way or other ſerve the Intereſt of Popery: And while theſe Princes ſtudyed only to ſerve themſelves and their own Humours, it is no wonder if they were ſerved but by few who did not the like, that is, more regarded their
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100584:27"/>own private Gain and Advancement, than the common Good of their Countrey. And though we have now a Prince of a quite different Temper, who induſtriouſly and vigorouſly proſecutes the Publick Good not only of theſe Kingdoms, but of his Neighbours and Confederates alſo, yet is he plainly under ſome difficulties by reaſon of the Perſons he found in Imployments, and whoſe Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he could not ſo well know 'till he had ſome tryal and experience of them: And therefore both the People of this Nation, and our Confederates have great reaſon to bear patiently our Diſappointments hitherto, in great hopes to ſee things in a better poſture another Year.</p>
            <p>But though this Experience may ſatisfie him of the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and good Qualifications of many, and of the Unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of others to be employed or truſted, yet will he ſtand in need of good Advice and Information concerning others to ſupply their Places; and the more by reaſon of the great Corruption of the Manners of this People by the laſt two Reigns, which hath tainted them (to ſay nothing here of other Immoralities) with Unfaithfulneſs, Greedineſs of Gain, and narrow-ſoul'd Selfiſhneſs, under ſuperficial Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances and plauſible Pretences, contrary to the true <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Genius, which is plain, honeſt, and truſty, and ſtout, hardy and induſtrious for the good of their Countrey. And it is, I doubt, too true, that thoſe who were neareſt in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or Employment to the Fountain of that Corruption, have been moſt infected by it: So that two things ſeem very neceſſary for the King, in this reſpect eſpecially, and in his Caſe, as they are indeed always for all Princes, who undertake great Enterprizes: The one to have the beſt <hi>Information</hi> he can; the other to uſe his own <hi>Liberty</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out confinement <hi>in the Choice</hi> of the fiteſt Perſons for his Service. Theſe are both for his own Intereſt; and being no leſs for the Intereſt of the Nation, they are alſo his Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; ſo that no Man who is a Friend either to him or his Countrey can be againſt it: And if due Care be taken but
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100584:28"/>to put the Navy and the Militia into good hands, I am well ſatisfied that he hath the great Body of the People ſo entire for him, that he may very well deſpiſe all ſuch Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear pretences of the Power of any Perſons or Parties, as ſome have ſuggeſted and publiſhed in Print. Nay, and this which I ſay (provided he make no Encroachment upon their Rights, and make but that Inſpection into Accounts, that they may ſee they are not unneceſſarily burden'd with Taxes, and keep the Sea clear, and an open and free Trade) will certainly more and more affect and unite the Hearts of all the People to him.</p>
            <p>There are two things by which crafty Courtiers uſe to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon Princes, (which in like manner are commonly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by unfaithful Servants with their Maſters of lower de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree) and thereby greatly abuſe both them and their Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for their own advantage. One is to divert them from too narrowly inſpecting Accounts and other Matters of State, by perſwading them that it is below them to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves much with ſuch matters. Another is, to keep them as much as may be from that Intelligence and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Affairs, which they might have in a free and enlarg'd compaſs of Converſation, by perſwading them that it is below their Majeſty to converſe much with any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their Nobility. But as no honeſt men will ever uſe or need ſuch Arts, ſo never was any Prince Great and Generous that would, or truly wiſe that could be ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd upon. <hi>True Majeſty</hi> is a Compoſition of Rightful Power, real Magnanimity of Mind in himſelf, and great Love and Eſteem in the Hearts of a People, grounded upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſick Worth and continual Communication thereof in ſtudying and induſtriouſly promoting the common Good and Welfare of a Nation. Without this State and Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, Guards and Ceremonies, and the External Enſigns of Majeſty; though they ſerve a little to awe and move ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration in rude and barbarous People, yet among more intelligent People, ſuch as are a great part of theſe Nations,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100584:28"/>they rather move indignation and diſdain, and ſerve but to alienate their minds the more from them who unworthily uſe them. And indeed for any Man much to regard them and pride himſelf in them, is a plain indication of a low and narrow Soul, ignorant of the true valuation of things. For all <hi>the Pride</hi> of Man is a lye, and the Product of Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and Folly; whereas the Truth and a right Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Worth and Uſe of things, cannot but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce at once thoſe noble Twins, the genuine Chriſtian <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility</hi> and true <hi>Magnanimity,</hi> with Contempt of thoſe mean things which the vulgar and little-great Men of the World admire. And beſides by Affability and a more free Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation a Prince engageth the Hearts of all; hath a more free and unconfin'd Intelligence and Information of things; hath the greater awe upon ſuch as are apt to impoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; hath an advantage to meet with better Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for his Service, than are like to be recommended by the heads of any narrow Faction; and by the Choice of ſuch as are beſt deſerving amongſt all, raiſeth an Emulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in others to qualifie themſelves better for the Service of himſelf and their Countrey: Whereas he who expects any great matter from theſe External Enſigns of Majeſty, without the Subſtance, will find it amount to no more in concluſion than the admiration of the moſt rude and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable part of the People, and that only while his Grandeur continues in its height, without any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diminution or Concuſſion.</p>
            <p>But here I muſt put all ſuch as have acceſs to their Prince in mind of a great Duty both to him and to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; that is, that laying aſide all Self-reſpect they conceal nothing from him which they think neceſſary for him to know, and comes properly in their way to acquaint him with, though there may be ſome Danger, that thereby they may incurr the Diſpleaſure of ſome great Courtier or Party. Every one will pretend that he is willing to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture his Life and his Eſtate for his King and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:100584:29"/>which is an indication that moſt Men have a ſenſe that it is their Duty ſo to do, as it is indeed: And were thoſe who pretend to that but honeſt and ſincere therein, there would not need many words to perſwade them to the conſcientions Diſcharge of this great Duty I am now ſpeaking of. For it is plainly a part of that Natural Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and Allegiance which we all owe to our King and our Countrey; and which all who have taken the Oath of Fidelity are doubly oblig'd to perform. And the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of it for fear of the diſpleaſure of any great Perſon or Party, is not only a piece of Baſeneſs and Cowardice but of Unfaithfulneſs to their King and Countrey; and, which is more than all this, even to God himſelf: It not only gives the Lye to their pretences of Loyalty, but it is fearing the Faces of Men more than God himſelf; and Diſtruſting his Protection in their doing their Duty, to which his Providence hath lead them.</p>
            <p>What I here recommend to others, I have hitherto in all Sincerity and Integrity practiſed my ſelf; and being well ſatisfied that I was lead thereunto by the ſpecial Providence of God, this very Conſideration of Fidelity hath been a great Motive to me to do as I have done: And therefore that with the ſame Fidelity and Integrity which I have uſed all along, I may bring theſe things, which I have been diſcourſing, to the point in hand, I muſt ſay plainly, that as our Fleets have been this Year baffled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the skill of any Vindicator to cover; ſo it is as plain, that the Fault was not in <hi>our Mariners or Seamen:</hi> For, to do them Right and Juſtice in this caſe, it is believed this Nation was never better provided with able Seamen; and it is certain, there is no part of the Nation more honeſt and firm for the Proteſtant Religion, the Proſperity and Honour of their Countrey, and the preſent Government: And thoſe who were at Sea, were as ready and zealous to have ſhewed ſo much in action, had they been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by their Officers. But though we be alſo as well
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:100584:29"/>furniſh'd with able Captains, (for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Genius, and ſuch a Trade as we have, doth naturally produce a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual ſtore of ſuch) yet were our Men of War generally filled with ſuch Captains and Officers, as few Merchants would intruſt with a Ship of Two hundred Tun. And I find it the common Opinion of moſt Seamen and Merchants I have diſcours'd with (and I have diſcours'd with many on purpoſe) that there are but few amongſt them that are any way qualified for that Service. And as this doth neceſſarily lead us to reflect upon the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of the Admiralty, and our Miniſters of State; ſo for ought I can perceive, it is the general Opinion of our Merchants and Seamen, that the Commiſſioners themſelves (be they who they will, for I know none of them) are as ill qualified for their undertaking, as the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers they employ; and that not only in reſpect of skill and ability, but it would tempt one to think in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Fidelity alſo, if that be true, which is much talked on, that there have bin <hi>Liſts offered</hi> to them of very able Seamen for Captains and Officers, who were very ready to have ſerved their King and Countrey, and the Common Cauſe, (though wanting not Employment or Eſtates they would neither purchaſe nor petition for any ſuch) yet were all neglected: That Commiſſions indeed have been offered to ſome, but ſo far beneath their Quality, that it may be thought rather a Trick to affront them, and make them refuſe, and then pretend they would not ſerve, than any honeſt intention to employ them: That, others who have been encouraged to raiſe men; when they had raiſed them and brought them up at no little charge, have themſelves and their men been turned off without any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. Certain it is, that this poor Nation hath been long devour'd and made a Prey of by a Company of gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Vermin, who have intruded into Offices without any ſenſe of the Service of the Publick, but meerly for their private advantage; and have uſed them accordingly: and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:100584:30"/>while we ſee the ſame evil Genius as buſie as ever, and ſuch Diſappointments, this is ſufficient ground of ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And therefore ſince ſuch things are talked on, it is fit they ſhould be look'd into: that if upon an honeſt Inquiry they be found to be true, they may be duly puniſh'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs'd for the future; and if not true, that the minds of the People may be ſatisfied upon good and ſolid grounds.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Puniſhment of what is paſt,</hi> it may be fit to look back into the Behaviour of ſome of our Gentlemen the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Summer, and particularly among the reſt that at <hi>Baintree-bay,</hi> which I find our Sea-men think not to have been ſuch as it ought. But for the Buſineſs of this Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, beſides the Conſideration of Juſtice and Prudence in other reſpects, the Eyes not only of all the Nation, but of all the World, are upon the King, to ſee how he will take it; ſo that he cannot in honour either neglect it, or ſuffer it to be palliated, and himſelf abuſed with ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences as will not paſs with Men of Underſtanding in the World. A Defeat in his Proſecution of this Matter might prove as diſhonourable to him, and almoſt as perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to his Intereſt, as the Diſappointment at Sea. And he hath the more reaſon to look to it, becauſe it is ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that other Matters have been ſo carried as might not be for his Honour or Intereſt, by falſe People about him.</p>
            <p>And for the <hi>Redreſs</hi> of theſe Matters <hi>for the future,</hi> to ſay nothing of the great Importance of it to the Nation, and to all his Confederates; and how greatly he is oblig'd both by God and Man, to take a ſpecial Care of it, certainly he can take no better Method than that which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready mention'd; laying aſide Ceremony and Complement, to ſend for ſome of the moſt intelligent Merchants, that are intire and hearty for him; and ſome of the moſt experienc'd and conſiderable Sea Captains and Commanders, who have been bred up in that Employment, and not corrupted in the late Reigns, and diſcourſe freely with them alone, and encourage them to be free to ſpeak their Opinions and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:100584:30"/>By this means he himſelf may come to a true un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding both of Matters and Perſons, and be able to make a better Choice than hath yet been, or is like to be made for him by others. And would he pleaſe to reſolve in time, to give Commiſſions to none but ſuch as by their own Intereſt among the Seamen were able to bring in moſt Men without Preſſing, and to all ſuch, we ſhould ſee matters ſoon well amended. This Nation at this time, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the wicked Ars which have been uſed to corrupt and debaſe it, doth not want Men fit for Great Actions, if proper Methods were uſed to invite them to it: But the Courſes which have been uſed of late, have been ſo well fitted to attract only the Scum and Froth of the Nation, that they may reaſonably be thought to have been introduc'd and promoted by ſuch as had no great kindneſs for it.</p>
            <p>What I have thus plainly and honeſtly diſcours'd, I doubt not but will be approv'd by God, and all wiſe and honeſt Men in the World; and may be of great uſe to the King, and to the Church, as well as to the whole Nation; if they pleaſe to make a good uſe of it; to begin ſpeedily, and in good earneſt lay ſuch a good Foundation, as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended in it; caſt out thoſe curſed Abominations, thoſe notorious Examples of Wickedneſs and Impiety, out of great Places, and provide ſome effectual Means for the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Manners of the reſt: Otherwiſe I doubt it may ſeal up ſome heavier Judgment than we have yet felt; in reſpect of which all our Diſappointments hitherto both at Sea and Land may prove but ſo many warnings. But as I wiſh, ſo I hope better things.</p>
            <p>I Intended for the Service of thoſe honeſt Perſons I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd before, <hi>Page</hi> 45. to have added that, which I hope might have extricated moſt of them out of thoſe Toyſs of Prejudice concerning the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſtitution and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which have intangled the Conſciences of many
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:100584:31"/>honeſt Men both formerly, and eſpecially ſince the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution; and to have ſhewed the Original Infuſion of that latent Poyſon which hath for a full Age and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicated the Heads of many otherwiſe learned and honeſt Men in our Church and Univerſities: But I am forced for want of leiſure to reſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve that for an <hi>APPENDIX,</hi> or a ſeparate Treatiſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100584:31"/>
            <head>A PREPARATION for DEATH, Recommended in A LETTER to a MALEFACTOR; But Uſeful for all ſorts of People.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sept.</hi> 7. 1690.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Mr. L</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Had really a kindneſs for you, becauſe I had good hopes of you, that you might become a good Man, if it pleaſed God to prolong your Life; and therefore have done already what I can for you, and ſhall be ready to do more, if it pleaſe God to give any opportunity. But becauſe I find your Caſe very dangerous in that reſpect, conſidering what hath been ſworn againſt you, and that this is not the firſt Fault, and there being great Complaints to the Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of the frequent Crimes that are committed of that kind; inſomuch that the Judge, who is a very good Man, and as tender of the Life of a Man, as is conſiſtent with his Duty, cannot ſhew you that Favour that otherwiſe he would, the greateſt Kindneſs that I can do you, is, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct you how to improve your preſent Circumſtances, which if you accordingly do, it will be ten thouſand times better than Life it ſelf. You muſt therefore know that <hi>the Great Buſineſs and End of our mortal Life</hi> in the Fleſh is to work the Creature by various Exerciſes to an entire Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Great Glorious and moſt Excellent Creator; who
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100584:32"/>is the Father of Spirits, and hath not only a juſt and abſolute Right and Dominion over us by Creation, Suſtentation and Redemption, but is in himſelf of ſo tranſcendent Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and ſo unconceivably Good and Gracious to his poor deſpicable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reatures (whereof the Love of Parents to their Children is but a little Repreſentation) that even Prudence and Gratitude, if it was well conſidered, would effectually prevail with a Man of Senſe to ſeek his Favour, though by the moſt Abſolute Subjection that can be conceived, were we not obliged to it by his Abſolute Dominion, and ſubject to his Irreſiſtable Power. And ſo that this entire Subjection be but effectually wrought in us, it matters not whether our Life be long or ſhort: Be it never ſo ſhort, if the Work be but perfectly done, it is the ſame thing as if it was longer; nay, in ſome reſpects better; for then it is ſecure; whereas till then it is in danger; only we are in the Hands of a Faithful Creator, and have continual Occaſion of Exerciſe of our Dependance upon him. Now to come to <hi>your parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Caſe:</hi> It ſeeems you have ran a Courſe directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; inſtead of exerciſing your ſelf to this Subjection, you perhaps have never in your Life been ſenſible of any ſuch Work you had to do; and not only not done any thing toward it, but done the quite contrary; inſtead of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting your Senſual Appetites to your Reaſon (which is the firſt part of this Exerciſe, and what all Mankind muſt account for) you have ſubjected the Man to the Beaſt in you, and abuſed your natural Faculties and Powers to ſerve and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie your Animal Affections; and inſtead of ſubjecting your Will to the Holy and Righteous External Declarations of the Will of God; you have yielded to the ſecret Motions of the Apoſtate Spirits in your Animal Affections in Diſobedience and Rebellion againſt that Holy Will of God. And by this means inſtead of promoting the great Buſineſs of your Life, you have run your ſelf into a worſe condition than when you were born and firſt began to live; ſo that thus much of your Life is not only loſt, but miſ-ſpent to your own Damage. And now to recover all again, and perfect this great Work, for which you had a longer Life aſſign'd you, in ſo ſhort a time as is now allowed you, you may think very
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100584:32"/>hard, if not impoſſible. But be of good comfort: Where Sin hath abounded, Grace hath much more abounded. God is able to do greater matters than this, if he be graciouſly ſo pleaſed, in leſs time; but then you muſt ſeek to him, and do what you can to prepare your ſelf for his Grace, and to be ready to cooperate with it faithfully. To this end you muſt endeavour to baniſh all thoughts of this World, and even of your Temporal Life it ſelf, and enter into ſerious Conſideration of the Great and Glorious Majeſty of God, who by his Wiſdom and Power hath Created and Governs the whole Univerſe, whereof the whole Earth in reſpect of the reſt is but as a drop of a Bucket, and in reſpect of him as nothing; and then conſider with your ſelf, what a deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable thing you are in compariſon of the Earth and all its Inhabitants, which yet altogether is ſo little as I have ſaid in reſpect of Almighty God; ſo deſpicable, if you were inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and righteous; and therefore that you ſhould be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatuated as to dare to tranſgreſs the leaſt of his Commands, doth juſtly deſerve not only Temporal Death, and to be cut off from the Children of Men, to whom you have been an Enemy, and Confederated with the Enemies of their Peace and Quiet, but Eternal Damnation, and to be for ever ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from his Glorious Preſence, againſt whom you have rebelled, and to have your part with thoſe Apoſtate Spirits, whoſe Motions you have obeyed, in eternal Miſery. And never ceaſe muſing and conſidering theſe great and plain Truths, and lifting up your Heart to God with fervent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and Prayers, that he will condeſcend to give you Grace, to enlighten your Mind, and molliſie your Heart with a deep Senſe of your miſerable Condition, till you find your ſelf ſo affected and concerned for the Favour of God and the Salvation of your Soul, that all Concern and Thought for your Temporal Life, as an inconſiderable thing in reſpect of that, may wholly ceaſe; and that your Soul be mightily humbled with a deep Senſe of your utter unworthineſs, that that Great and Glorious and moſt Holy Majeſty ſhould have any regard to ſo deſpicable and ſo ſinful a Wretch, with great Indignation againſt your Sin and Madneſs, and againſt thoſe curſed Apoſtate Spirits, which by their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100584:33"/>Impreſſions have preſſed you on into all this Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Miſchief. When you have gotten thus far, thoſe wicked Spirits, when they find they can no longer keep you in Darkneſs and Impenitence, will ſtrive to thruſt you head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into Deſpair, and poſſeſs you with dreadful Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of the Holineſs, Juſtice, and Severity of God. And therefore you muſt further know, that this Great and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Majeſty, though moſt Holy, Righteous and Terrible to the Impenitent and Incorrigible, yet is of unconceivable Mercy, Clemency and Goodneſs to truly humble and peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Sinners: And though he be a God of ſuch Holineſs and Purity that there is no immediate Acceſs to him for ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicable and polluted Creatures as the Children of Men, yet hath he in his great Mercy and Wiſdom provided a moſt admirable Expedient, whereby we may have acceſs to him at all times with Confidence and Aſſurance of Acceptance; and not only Pardon of Sin, but Grace alſo, and Divine Power to ſerve him acceptably. And this is by Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, God and Man united in one Perſon, who having run the ſame Race and Exerciſe of Subjection by Obedience even to Death, and the moſt ſhameful Death, the Death of the Croſs, and thereby obtained Favour for us with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, him hath God exalted to be Judge both of Quick and Dead, and to be a Prince and a Saviour to all that obey him, and are united to him by his Spirit reſiding and ruling in their Hearts. Him hath God propoſed to be a Propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for us by his Paſſion and Death, and raiſed up to be a Mediator and an Advocate for us with him in Heaven; and by him, and in his Name, all who are Seal'd with, and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his Spirit, have Acceſs and certain Acceptance with the Father. But that you may be one of theſe, here is again, as before, ſomething to be done by you. You muſt ruminate much upon the admirable Clemency and Goodneſs of God to his poor Creatures, for the recovery of them out of a moſt miſerable Slavery to the Powers of Darkneſs; and how admirable a Perſon this Chriſt Jeſus is, who having performed a perfect Obedience to the Father in our Nature, and by his Paſſion conſecrated it, and exalted it to Heaven to be there as a Magnet to attract all who receive him, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100584:33"/>give up themſelves to obey him: And how great a new Obligation this is upon us to do ſo: How great and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Benefit and Advantage is to our ſelves: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how much common Prudence and Gratitude ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with you for that purpoſe. And never ceaſe muſing and thinking thereupon, and lifting up your Heart to God in earneſt Deſires and Prayers in the Name of Chriſt Jeſus, and for his Sake, that he will be pleaſed to enlighten your Mind with a clear underſtanding of theſe admirable Truths, and fill your Heart with ſuch Love and Admiration of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſo demonſtrated in this admirable Perſon, that all things in this World, your Temporal Life in the Fleſh, and all that you are or have, may appear to you, as in truth they are, very mean and deſpicable, and nothing valuable and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable but Chriſt Jeſus, and an inſeparable Union with him; till you find your Heart ſo affected with theſe things, that you become intirely reſigned in all things to the Will of God, be willing and even deſirous to be Partaker of the Sufferings of that Holy and Innocent Perſon, which you have juſtly deſerved, and with full purpoſe of Heart give up your ſelf to an entire Subjection, Obedience and Service of the Holy Trinity, to whom you have been dedicated in your Baptiſm, to all Eternity. This is a great Work indeed; but God is able to do this, and more than we can ask or think, in leſs time than you have to prepare for it: And if he will be ſo gracious to you, you will be a happy Creature, and have reaſon to admire and bleſs his Holy Providence, and abundant Grace, which by ſo admirable Means hath brought you to it; and then you will have nothing more to do, but to perform ſome other Works of true Repentance, which I ſhall preſently ſhew you, and wait upon God and ſtand rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for what-ever he ſhall call you to. Theſe remaining Works of Repentance reſpect either the particular Perſons you have wronged, or the State and your Country in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. To the particular Perſons you muſt make Reſtitution as far as you are able, pray to God to make up what is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by his Grace and Bleſſing to them, and ſend to them and deſire their Pardon; and heartily forgive all who have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured you, acknowledging them, what-ever they intended,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100584:34"/>to have been God's Inſtruments for your juſt Puniſhment and Correction, and pray heartily to God to pardon them. And to the State and your Country you muſt do what you can to make Satisfaction and Reſtitution by theſe means: You muſt do what you can to break thoſe wicked Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Confederations and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ractices, by making all the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery you can both of Robberies and ſuch like Practices, and of the Perſons who either uſe ſuch Practices, or harbor, or are any way Partners with them therein. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus much I ſhall adviſe you, that you do it in Charity, not only to your Country, but even to the Malefactors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſo as that they may be reclaimed if poſſible; and therefore do it not to any one, but to ſuch as you think moſt like to uſe your Diſcoveries wiſely and charitably, with due care and reſpect even to them. And if you deſire my Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance therein, I will endeavour to come to you on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, rather than you ſhall want Aſſiſtance. I have no more now but my Prayers for you to Almighty God, that he will bleſs theſe Inſtructions, make them effectual upon you, and by his powerful Grace perfect this great and good Work in your Soul.</p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>IT is a <hi>common Opinion among Malefactors,</hi> that it is a <hi>diſhonourable</hi> thing, and therefore odious and deteſtable, <hi>to diſcover,</hi> (which they call betraying) <hi>their Companions or Partners in their Crimes.</hi> But this is plainly a mere vulgar Error, and a groſs Miſtake, and no leſs pernicious to themſelves, and to their Partners, than to their Country, and Mankind in General. The <hi>Fallacy</hi> lies in the Miſapplication of a true Principle. For the true reaſon why Breach of Faith and Betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Truſt is ſo odious a thing among all Men, is, becauſe it is not only injurious to the Perſon, but tends to the diſturbance of Humane Society: So that if it was generelly practis'd, Men would not know how to deal one with another, and would be deprived of mutual Aſſiſtance in many caſes, and of one of the greateſt Comforts of Humane Life. But yet, as in many other Caſes, that which in the General is unlawful, diſhonourable and odious, (as the taking away the Life of a Man) may in a particular caſe, under ſome certain Circumſtances, become a neceſſary and commendable Duty, (as the Condemnation and Execution of a Murderer, which is an Act both of Juſtice upon the Malefactor, and of Charity to the reſt of Mankind, by preventing and diſcouraging other Murders) ſo it is in this: To
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100584:34"/>diſcover a Secret committed to ones Truſt, which may lawfully be concealed; but eſpecially, to do it for ones own advantage, and to the prejudice of his Conſident, is commonly reputed, and very juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a very baſe, unmanly, diſhoneſt and diſhonourable thing. But when the Secret or Conſidence is in a thing wicked and unjuſt, inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to other Perſons, and to the Society whereof a Man is a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as, to his Country; this is no ſuch Secret as can honeſtly be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed; becauſe it is a Breach of Charity to the injured Perſons, and a Violation of that Faith, which, by an antecedent and greater Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, is due to the whole Society, whereof he is a Member. Such mutual Confidences therefore are not properly Human Societies, but a kind of Confederacies of Enemies and Diſturbers of the proper Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, Peace and Welfare of Men, tending to the Deſtruction thereof. And the Hypotheſis upon which they are built is for the ſame reaſon plainly a Deluſion, and probably a Stratagem of the Apoſtate Spirits and Enemies of Mankind, to ſtrengthen their Party and Intereſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Men; ſo that as on the one hand this is no ſuch Truſt, as it is diſhonourable to any Perſon to break it, becauſe it is a wicked thing to engage in it; ſo on the other hand it is a Breach of Faith and Duty to the Society not to break but conceal it, and thereby ſupport a Confederacy of Enemies and Diſturbers of the Peace of his Country; ſo that the Perſon, who conceals what he knows of that nature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes acceſſary, even after his Death, to all the Evils which are afterward committed, and might have been prevented by his Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. Bendes an obſtinate and wilful Concealment even to the Death, is not only a Confirmation of that particular wicked Confederacy wherein the Perſon is engaged, or any way concerned or acquainted, but tends mightily to harden others, and ſo to ſupport all ſuch wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Confederacies in general. Whereas did ſuch Perſons, at leaſt when apprehended, in their Affliction become ſerious, and not ſuffer themſelves to be longer abuſed and impoſed upon by ſuch a vulgar Error and Diabolical Deluſion, but conſider well, judge rightly, and act accordingly, ſuch wicked Confederacies could not ſubſiſt for want of mutual Confidence. Nor is ſuch Concealment only injurious to divers other particular Perſons, and a Violation of that Faith and Love, which all Men owe to their Country; but very pernicious, and of <hi>evil conſequence to the Partners, and all other ſuch Criminals;</hi> becauſe it encourageth them to venture upon and perſiſt in ſuch Courſes as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve them more and more in Sin, whereby they treaſure up Wrath againſt the Day of Wrath; and expoſe them to all thoſe temporal Evils, which uſually firſt or laſt over-take them. Whereas by ſuch a Diſcovery, as I have recommended, the Perſons diſcovered might poſſibly be reclaimed and brought to Repentance, at leaſt might be hindered from ſo much increaſing their Score, which were better for them, though by an unnatural and otherwiſe untimely Death, than
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100584:35"/>that they ſhould longer protract a miſerable Life here to the increaſe of their Miſery hereafter. Nor is it leſs <hi>pernicious to the Malefactor himſelf.</hi> For as without true Repentance no Pardon can be expected with God: So whoever doth not all he can to make Reſtitution, and repair all the Evil and Damage he hath done, and to prevent all he can for the future, can be no true Penitent, holding ſtill an implicit Confederacy at leaſt, with wickedneſs. And as he can expect no Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from God, ſo is he to be looked upon by Men, not as a Man of Honor in any reſpect, but as a reprobate, deluded, and hardned Wretch, an Enemy to Man-kind, and a Confederate with Death and Hell, and the Kingdom of Darkneſs; an odious and deteſtable Creature, inſted of being in the leaſt honourable as he vainly fancied. That, which only is Honourable or Commendable in ſuch Caſe, and the only true Wiſdom, is, 1. To conſider ſeriouſly the unreaſonableneſs and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of the Crime, till ſuch conſideration hath produced a juſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and Abhorrence of it. 2. To acknowledge ingenuouſly his own Folly and Impotence to yield to and be overcome by ſuch a Temptation, what-ever it was, which induced him to it; and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more manly to have born any hardſhips of a tranſitory human Life, than ſo baſely to have violated the Order of the Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which aſſigned thoſe hardſhips for his Exerciſe, and the Laws of his Country. 3. To give Glory to God, acknowledging the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of his Puniſhment, and the ſpecial Providence of God, who hath brought him to it not only in Juſtice, but in Mercy too, to cut off his Sin, for Correction of his Miſcarriages, and that he may not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned with the World, if he truly and effectually repent, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore directed. 4. To endeavour, as far as poſſible he can, to break all ſuch Confederacies, and prevent all the Miſchief which might o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be committed by a plain Diſcovery of all he knoweth. This indeed would be an Evidence of ſuch a Change and Diſpoſition of Mind, as is really valuable in the Judgment of all Good and Wiſe Men, and acceptable in the ſight of Almighty God, and therefore truly Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable with others, and the trueſt wiſdom for himſelf.</p>
               <p>What I have here ſaid to Criminals is fit to be conſidered by all who have any knowledge of any ſuch Crimes. That which they may fancy to be Faithfulneſs, or Charity, or Pity to Criminals, is a great Miſtake and Deluſion, and in truth Unfaithfulneſs and want of due regard to their Country. That Malefactors be brought to condign Puniſhment both Juſtice and Charity to our Country require; which is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the Conſideration of any particular Perſon: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to hinder, or reſuſe ones Aſſiſtance to it, is to prefer a Malefactor, and deſert the Duty he ows his Country. But in other reſpects Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity and Humanity requires more to be done for them, than uſually is with us.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="act">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100584:35"/>
            <head>AN ACT FOR The more effectual Reſtraining and Suppreſſing of divers notorious Sins, and Reformation of the Manners of the People of this Nation.</head>
            <p>WHereas the Advancement of the Honour and Service of Almighty God, and of the Proteſtant Religion, which by his wonderful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence hath been Eſtabliſhed and Preſerved in theſe Nations, ought <hi>at all times</hi> to be the Chief Part of the Care <hi>as well of the Legiſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive as Executive Power of this Kingdom; but more eſpecially at this time, after ſo admirable a Deliverance from ſo great and apparent Danger as lately threatned us:</hi> And <hi>for that End</hi> a General Reformation of the Lives and Manners <hi>of all degrees of People</hi> of this Nation, is earneſtly deſired by <hi>all good men, and by all Means to be endeavoured,</hi> as that which muſt Eſtabliſh <hi>both the Church and State,</hi> and ſecure to all their Religion, Happineſs and Peace: All which ſeem to be in great Danger at this time, by reaſon of the Overflowing of Vice, which is too notorious in this as well as other neighbouring Nations, and more particularly the Sins of <hi>Blaſphemy, Prophane Swearing</hi> and <hi>Curſing, Perjury, Prophanation</hi> of the <hi>Lords Day, Adultery, Fornication,</hi> and <hi>Drunkenneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore for the better carrying on of ſo good a Work, and for the more effectual preventing, correcting and ſuppreſſing of the Horrid and Helliſh ſins of <hi>BLASPHEMIE</hi> and prophane <hi>Swearing</hi> and <hi>Curſing:</hi> Be it En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the King and Queens Majeſty, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by the Authority of the ſame, That if any Perſon not diſturbed in Brain by Sickneſs or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ſhall at any time hereafter preſume in word or writing to Blaſpheme, or ſpeak or write contemptuouſly or ſcoffingly of God bleſſed for ever, his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour Chriſt Jeſus, the Holy Spirit, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100584:36"/>Scriptures, the Chriſtian Religion, or any of them, the Perſon and perſons in whoſe preſence or hearing ſuch Offence ſhall be committed, ſhall and are hereby required preſently to ſet down the Words expreſſing the ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſence, or ſo much thereof as he or they can remember, and the manner thereof, in writing; and to give notice and teſtifie his and their Knowledge thereof upon Oath within the ſpace of ten dayes, unto ſome Juſtice of the Peace of the County or Place where the ſame ſhall be committed, who is hereby authorized and required to adminiſter the ſaid Oath, and to take the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the ſaid perſons in writing. And every Juſtice of the Peace, who ſhall have any knowledge of any ſuch Offence committed, either by his own hearing or view, or by any ſuch Teſtimony, or by Confeſſion of the Party, is hereby authorized and required to cauſe the ſaid Offender to become bound to appear and anſwer for the ſame at the next general Gaol-delivery or <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner</hi> to be holden for that County, and to be of Good Behaviour in in the mean time. And likewiſe to cauſe the ſaid Witneſs and witneſſes to be bound over to proſecute and give Evidence againſt the ſaid Offender, who at the ſaid next Gaol-delivery or <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer</hi> if it may be, or otherwiſe as ſoon as may be, ſhall be Indicted for his ſaid Offence, and upon the Tryall being found Guilty, ſhall forfeit the ſum of one moiety thereof to the King and Queen, their Heirs and Succeſſors, and the other moiety thereof to the Proſecutor, and ſhall by the Judge, before whom ſuch Tryal ſhall be had, be committed to the Gaol, there to remain till he or ſhe ſhall have paid the ſaid ſum, and ſhall become bound with two good Sureties to the Good Behaviour for the ſpace of ſeven years then next enſuing, in caſe it be the Parties firſt Offence of that kind: but if it be the ſecond Offence of which he is ſo convicted, then to be of the Good Behaviour during Life. And if it be a third Offence and Conviction, then the Offendor ſhall be committed to the Gaol, there to remain till he or ſhe ſhall abjure the Realm.</p>
            <p>And be it likewiſe enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That all and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Perſon and Perſons who ſhall hereafter offend by <hi>PROPHANE SWEARING</hi> or <hi>CURSING,</hi> ſhall forfeit and pay for every ſuch Offence to the uſe of the Poor of the Pariſh where the ſame ſhall be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or if it be out of any Pariſh, to the uſe of the Poor of ſuch next ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning Pariſh as the Juſtice or Juſtices hereafter mentioned ſhall appoint, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Degree, and Quality of the Perſon offending, in Manner and Form following, that is to ſay, every Peer and Baron of this Realm, or other the Kings Dominions reſiding here, and every Perſon holding and enjoying any Barony, the ſumm of twenty ſhillings, every Baronet and Knight the ſumm of thirteen ſhillings and four pence, every Eſquire, and every Perſon having and enjoying any Office, Place, Dignity, Promotion, or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, of the value of one hundred pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> or more, the ſumm of Ten ſhillings, and every Gentleman and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100584:36"/>in Holy Orders, every Graduate in either <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, and every Perſon having and enjoying any Office, Place, Dignity, Promotion, or Employment, Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, under one hundred pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> the ſumm of ſix ſhillings and eight pence; and every perſon keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Publick Houſe of Entertainment, and every other Perſon under the degree of a Gentleman, (except Labourers and poor people) the ſumm of five ſhillings, and every Labourer and other poor perſon, the ſumm of two ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and ſix-pence; and every married Woman or Widow, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Degree and Quality of her preſent or laſt Husband, and in caſe ſhe was never Married, according to the degree and quality of a younger Son of her Father. All which ſumms and forfeitures all and every perſon and perſons in whoſe preſence or hearing any ſuch Offence ſhall be committed, are hereby Authorized and required to demand for the uſe of the Poor of the ſaid Pariſh, and in caſe the ſame ſhall be paid, to pay it over immediately to the Overſeers of the Poor for the uſe aforeſaid. And in caſe the perſon ſo offending ſhall upon ſuch demand refuſe to pay the ſumm by him ſo forfeited, then the ſaid perſons in whoſe preſence or hearing the ſaid Offence ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, ſhall, and are hereby required preſently thereupon to put the words expreſſing the Offence into Writing, under his and their Hands, and to give notice of the ſaid Offence, demand and refuſal, and to teſtifie his or their knowledge thereof upon Oath within the ſpace of ten dayes unto ſome Juſtice of the Peace, of the County or Place where the ſame Offence ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, who is hereby authorized and required to adminiſter the ſaid Oath, and thereupon (unleſs the Offendor be a Peer, or ſuch other great Man of this Realm, as in this Act hereafter is mentioned) to direct and ſend his Warrant to the Conſtable, Tythingman, Church-Wardens and Overſeers of the poor of ſuch Pariſh as aforeſaid, or of the Pariſh where the Offendor ſhall inhabit, thereby commanding them or ſome one or more of them to levy the ſumm and ſumms ſo forfeited for the uſe of the poor of ſuch pariſh as aforeſaid, and likewiſe the like ſumm to be paid to ſuch Witneſs and Witneſſes, for his and their time, travel and pains employed about any ſuch Information, by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs and ſale of the Goods of ſuch Offendor, rendering unto him or her the overplus: And in caſe no ſuch Diſtreſs can be had, to apprehend the ſaid Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, and him or her to bring before the ſaid Juſtice or ſome other Juſtice of the Peace of the ſaid County or place, who is hereby required to commit the ſaid Offendor to the common Gaol, there to remain until the ſaid Offendor ſhall have paid the ſeveral ſumms aforeſaid, and full Costs and Charges to be taxed by the ſaid Juſtice for Apprehending and Conveying of ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendors to the Gaol, if it be the firſt Conviction for ſuch Offence: But if the ſaid Offendor ſhall have been before convicted as aforeſaid of the like Offence and obſtinate Refuſal, then to remain there until the ſaid Offendor ſhall moreover become bound before the Juſtices of the Peace at their General Quarter Seſſions, or the Judge of Aſſize, General Gaol Delivery, or <hi>Oyer</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100584:37"/>and <hi>Terminer,</hi> to be of the Good Behaviour for the ſpace of then next enſuing. But in caſe it ſhall appear to the ſaid Juſtice, by Confeſſion of the party, or otherwiſe, that the Offendor ſo convicted is not able to pay the ſaid ſever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l ſumms, then the ſaid Offender ſhall be ſet in the Stocks for three whole hours for his firſt Offence, and ſhall be ſo ſet in the Stocks, and moreover be publickly whip'd, not exceeding ten laſhes for the ſecond, and every other Offence afterward.</p>
            <p>And becauſe it is found by common Experience, that Exceſs in Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doth, beſides other inconveniences, very much diſpoſe people to profane Swearing; and that ſuch Exceſſes are uſually promoted by <hi>DRINKING HEALTHS:</hi> Be it therefore enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that every perſon who ſhall begin or pledge any Health, ſhall forfeit and pay as is before enacted for prophane Swearing, to be levyed in like manner, and for the ſame <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes; and all perſons preſent required to demand the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, and give Information of the Refuſal, if any be, as in the ſaid Caſe is appointed, and the Juſtice thereupon to proceed accordingly.</p>
            <p>Provided, and it is hereby further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That if any <hi>Peer</hi> of the Realm, <hi>Prelate,</hi> or other perſon expreſſed in the Statute of <hi>2 Ri. 2.</hi> entituled, <hi>The Penalty for telling of ſlanderous Lyes of the great Men of the Realm,</hi> or any Baron of the Exchequer, upon committing any ſuch Offence of Prophane Swearing or Curſing, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, ſhall refuſe to pay the Penalty thereby forfeited, being demanded as aforeſaid, the Juſtice of the Peace before whom ſuch Information ſhall be given, ſhall cauſe a Copy of the ſaid Information to be delivered to the ſaid Offender, his Lady or Steward, and ſhall bind over the Witneſs and Witneſſes to proſecute and give Evidence of the ſaid Offence, Demand and Refuſal at the next Gaol-Delivery, or <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer</hi> to be holden for the County, or Diviſion. Where ſuch Offendor having notice as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, ſhall be obliged to appear and Travers his Endictment. And in caſe he ſhall not appear, or upon his Appearance and Travers ſhall be found Guilty, he ſhall incurr the ſeveral Diſabilities hereafter mentioned, and forfeit the ſumm of twenty pounds, one moity to the King and Queen, and the other to the Proſecutor or Proſecutors.</p>
            <p>And becauſe it may be feared that <hi>Perjury</hi> is often committed in this Nation by the Neglect of Officers and perſons ſworn to the due performance of their Offices, Places, and Employments, or Duties: Be it therefore En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the Authority aforeſaid, for the preventing the like for the future, that every wilful neglect after the <hi>24th.</hi> day of <hi>June</hi> next, of any Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer or other perſon, duly ſworn to the performance of any Office, Place, Employment, or Duty, in the due performance thereof, ſhall be deemed and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged Perjury, and be proſecuted and puniſhed as other Perjury by the Law of this Land.</p>
            <p>And for the more effectual Execution of the Statutes heretofore made for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100584:37"/>the Reformation of ſundry Abuſes, and better Obſervation of the <hi>LORDS DAY,</hi> commanly called <hi>Sunday,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 Car. 1 c. 2 29 Car. 2. c 7.</note> be it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That all and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Conſtable, Tythingman, Headborough, Church Warden, and Overſeer of the poor, and other Officers in their reſpective Pariſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, may and are hereby authorized and required upon notice of any Offence contrary to the ſaid Statutes, or either of them, immediately to repair to the place where any ſuch Offence is ſaid to be committed, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their own view thereof, without any Warrant from any Juſtice of Peace to ſeize all ſuch Goods as they ſhall at any time find expoſed to ſale, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the ſaid Statutes or either of them, and to diſpoſe thereof as by the ſaid Statutes, or either of them is directed; and likewiſe to ſtop, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, and ſecure all perſons offending againſt the ſaid Statutes, or either of them, and them to carry before ſome Juſtice of the Peace, to be dealt with according to the Law, unleſs the ſaid Offendor and Offenders ſhall forthwith pay the penalty forfeited by the ſaid Statutes to ſuch Officer or Officers.</p>
            <p>And for ſuppreſſing of the brutiſh Sins of <hi>ADULTERY</hi> and <hi>FOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NICATION,</hi> Be it alſo enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That if any Man after the tenth day of <hi>June,</hi> in this preſent year of our Lord, <hi>1690.</hi> ſhall have the carnal knowledge of the Body of any Woman other than his Wife, (except in the caſe of a Rape,) or ſhall be found in Bed, or in any ſuch poſture of Nakedneſs, with any other Woman than his Wife, from which it may be reaſonably preſum'd that any ſuch Act of carnal Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation was committed by the ſaid parties, either of the ſaid parties being at the ſame time in the State of lawful Matrimony with any other perſon not abſent beyond the Seas, or otherwiſe unknown to the ſaid party to be living, by the ſpace of ſeven years, the ſame ſhall be taken, reputed, and adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed lawful and ſufficient Evidence of <hi>ADULTERY,</hi> and the ſaid par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties being thereof convicted by Verdict upon Indictment or preſentment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Judge or Juſtices of Gaol Delivery, or <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> ſhall ſuffer Death as in caſe of Felony, without benefit of Clergy: But if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſaid parties be at the ſame time in ſuch State of Matrimony, the ſame ſhall be taken, reputed, and adjudged lawful and ſufficient Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Fornication only, for which being thereof convicted as aforeſaid, each of the ſaid parties ſhall for every ſuch Offence be committed to the common Gaol without Bail or Mainprize, there to continue for the ſpace of and further until he or ſhe reſpectively ſhall give Security, to be taken by one or more Juſtice or Juſtices of the Peace of the ſaid County or place, to be of the Good Behaviour for the ſpace of Year then next enſuing, if it be the firſt Offence, but if the ſecond for the ſpace of Years, and if the third during life.</p>
            <p>Provided that no Attainder by vertue hereof ſhall extend to Corruption
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100584:38"/>of Blood, or forfeiture of the Eſtate real or Perſonal of the perſon ſo at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted.</p>
            <p>And for the better preventing of the ſaid Sins for the time to come, be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That the Conſtable, or Tythingman, and the Church-Wardens of every pariſh for the time being, ſhall once eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Month at leaſt, or oftener if they ſee cauſe, make diligent enquiry through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their reſpective Pariſhes, to diſcover all perſons who ſhall proſtitute themſelves as common Strumpets, and ſhall certifie the Names, or reputed Names, and the places of abode of all ſuch perſons as they ſhall find either by Information of Neighbours, or other probable circumſtances to be ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in that reſpect, unto ſome Juſtice of the Peace reſiding in or near their reſpective Pariſhes, who upon receipt of ſuch Certificate, ſhall direct his Warrant to the Conſtable or Officer of the Pariſh where any ſuch ſuſpected perſon ſhall be found, to bring before him all or any ſuch ſuſpected perſon or perſons: And ſhall examine her or them, and ſuch Witneſſes as ſhall appear in their behalf, concerning their way and courſe of livelihood. And that all ſuch perſons ſo ſuſpected, and not being able to give a good account of themſelves, ſhall be puniſhed as Vagabonds, and ſturdy Beggars are liable to be puniſhed by vertue of the Statute made in the <hi>39th</hi> year of the Reign of the late Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in that behalf.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted, that all ſuch Perſons as ſhall keep Houſes of Bawdry, or wittingly and knowingly admit lewd Perſons, Men and Women, into their Houſes to Commit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, or ſhall receive, or continue to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain in their Houſes as Lodgers or otherwiſe any common Strumpet, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſhe continueth ſuch her lewd Courſe of Life, or ſhall wittingly and knowingly procure Meetings between Men and Women in order to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Adultery or Fornication together, ſhall forfeit for the firſt Offence the ſumme of <hi>5 l.</hi> and for the ſecond the ſumme of <hi>10 l.</hi> together with Coſts of Suit to be recovered by Action of Debt, Bill, plaint or Information, at the ſuit of ſuch Perſon as will proſecute for the ſame, to and for his or their own uſe, in which no Eſſoyn, Protection or Wager of Law ſhall be allowed: And in default of ſuch proſecution within ſix Months after each ſeveral Offence, ſhall forfeit the like ſumm and ſumms, being thereof Convicted by Preſentment or Indictment before the Juſtices of the Peace at the Quarter Seſſions to be held for ſuch County, Diviſion, or Place where any ſuch Offence ſhall happen to be committed as aforeſaid: One moi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty to the King, and the other to the Poor of the Pariſh where the Offence ſhall be committed. And moreover for ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Offence ſhall be ſet in the Pillory in the next Market-Town or open Place: And for the third Offence upon Conviction ſhall abjure the Realm.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted for the end and purpoſe aforeſaid, that no Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever keeping or that keep any publick Tavern, Ale-houſe, Tipling-houſe, or other Houſe of common Entertainment within the Cities of <hi>London</hi> or <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> or Burrough of <hi>Southwark,</hi> or places adjacent, ſhall keep any
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100584:38"/>Organ or other Inſtrument or Inſtruments of Muſick for the Entertainment of Gueſts, on pain of forfeiting the ſumme of <hi>20 l.</hi> being thereof lawfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed upon Preſentment or Indictment at the Quarter-ſeſſions of the Peace, and upon the further penalty of being diſabled to ſell Ale, Wine, or other Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors by Retail for the ſpace of a twelve Month after ſuch Conviction. And every perſon ſo convicted and yet ſelling any ſuch liquors, contrary to this Act, ſhall be puniſhed as ſelling the ſame without Licenſe.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that if any Women or Woman ſhall at any time after Sun-ſet and before Sun-riſing be entertain'd or received into any Tavern, Ale-houſe, or other publick Houſe of Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment as Gueſt or Gueſts (except in Caſe of Travellers received into their Inns) then the Maſter, Miſtriſs or Dame of ſuch Tavern or Houſe upon proof thereof made before one or more Juſtice or Juſtices of the Peace ſhall forfeit <hi>40 s.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs the ſaid Maſter, Miſtriſs or Dame, ſhall prove by good and ſufficient Teſtimony, that ſuch Woman and Women are of good Behaviour and Reputation: And if afterwards the ſaid Maſter, Miſtreſs or Dame, ſhall permit the like Offence, the ſaid Tavern or Houſe ſhall be taken and deem'd a Bawdy-houſe, and the ſaid Maſter, Miſtriſs and Dame, ſhall be puniſhed as Keeper thereof.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that if any Offender within this Act ſhall <hi>not</hi> be Convicted and <hi>Puniſhed by the Juſtice of Peace,</hi> nor proſecuted at the Suit of any Party, as is by this Act directed within the ſpace of Months after the Offence committed, that then the ſaid Offender ſhall and may be <hi>Proſecuted at the Quarter-Seſſions</hi> of the Peace, or at the Aſſizes holden for the County where the Offence is committed, by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment or Information within one Year after the Offence committed.</p>
            <p>And be it alſo Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that when and as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as any Perſon ſhall be Convicted upon Indictment for any Offence contrary to this Act, the Judge, Juſtice and Juſtices before whom the Conviction ſhall be, ſhall immediately thereupon <hi>ſignifie the ſame to the Biſhop of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs</hi> where the Offence ſhall be committed, to the end that he may thereupon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to <hi>EXCOMMUNICATION</hi> of the Offender, who ſhall not be abſolved but by ſpecial Order of the Biſhop, upon Certificate by the Parſon or Vicar, and Church-Wardens of the Pariſh where the Offender ſhall inhabit, that the ſaid Offender ſhall on ſome Lords-Day in the Morning immediately after the Creed appointed for the Communion Service, in the body or greateſt Ile of the ſaid Pariſh Church have publickly confeſſed his or her Offence, and ſolemnly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his or her unfeigned Sorrow and Repentance for the ſame.</p>
            <p>And be it alſo Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that no Perſon Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated or bound to be of Good Behaviour, or Convicted of any Crime or Offence by Virtue or in purſuance of this Act, ſhall be admitted to Vote or ſit in Parliament, or be capable to be Elected to ſerve in Parliament, or to Act as Judge, Juſtice of the Peace, or Miniſter of Juſtice, or to perform any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Eccleſiaſtical Office within the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> or Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:100584:39"/>or to maintain any Action of the Caſe for Scandalous Words, or upon the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute <hi>de Scandalis Magnatum,</hi> until he ſhall be duely diſcharged of his Scouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the good Behaviour, and be abſolved from his Excommunication as aforeſaid; and ſhall have paid and performed all Forfeitures, Pains, Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Coſts and Charges, incurred, forfeited, taxed or impoſed by Virtue of this Act, any Priviledge of Parliament or other whatever in any wiſe not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided that no Perſon excommunicate by Vertue or in purſuance of this Act, ſhall by reaſon of any ſuch Excommunication incurr or ſuffer any other temporal Puniſhment, Diſability or Incommodity than is by this Act appointed or Ordained, any Law, Statute, Canon, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage or Cuſtom to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the Effect of all Laws, and the Honour of the Government in that reſpect doth depend upon the due Execution thereof, to the end that this Act may be the more effectually put in Execution, be it Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforeſaid, that the ſame ſhall be <hi>publickly read</hi> in all Cathedral Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiate and Pariſh Churches, and in all Chappels, where the Common Prayers uſually are or ought to be read, immediately after the Creed appointed for the Communion Service, on ſome Lords-Day before the <hi>24th.</hi> day of <hi>June</hi> next, and afterwards once every Year upon the ſecond Lords-Day in <hi>March;</hi> and that for that purpoſe it ſhall be provided by the Church-Wardens of every Pariſh, at the charge of their reſpective Pariſhes: And that all <hi>Conſtables, Tything-men, Headboroughs and Church-wardens</hi> ſhall at the time of their Entrance upon their reſpective Offices be <hi>Sworn to put this Act in due Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,</hi> and to give Information of all Offences committed in their reſpective Pariſhes, or by any perſon of the ſame Pariſh contrary to this Act, or to the Statutes againſt <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> unto ſome Juſtice of the Peace of the ſame County or Place within ten Dayes after the ſame ſhall come to their knowledge, according to their beſt Skill and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding: And alſo that this Act ſhall be <hi>given in Charge</hi> to the Grand Jury by the Judges and Juſtices at their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Aſſizes and Quarter-Seſſions, to enquire and preſent the ſeveral Offences aforeſaid, and all Neglects of Juſtices, Conſtables, Church-Wardens and other Officers and Perſons in the due Execution thereof.</p>
            <p>And be it alſo Enacted, that the Judge, Juſtice and Juſtices, before whom any Perſon ſhall be Convicted of any Offence by Vertue of this Act, ſhall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and cauſe to be paid unto ſuch Proſecutor and Proſecutors, as ſhall other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe receive no benefit by this Act, and to the ſeveral Witneſſes, ſuch reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Coſts and Charges,</hi> and in ſuch manner, as he or they ſhall think fit: And that in any <hi>Action brought</hi> againſt any Juſtice, Conſtable, or other Officer or Perſon for any thing done by Vertue or in purſuance of this Act, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant may <hi>Plead the General Iſſue,</hi> and give the ſpecial matter in Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and upon Verdict for him or Non-ſuit of the Plaintiff ſhall recover his treble Coſts.</p>
            <trailer>The END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100584:39"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
